<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A School for princes, or, Political reflections upon three conspiracies preceding the death of Alexander the Great translated out of French by A.O.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 95 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14690</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12541535</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12541535</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 291:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A School for princes, or, Political reflections upon three conspiracies preceding the death of Alexander the Great translated out of French by A.O.</title>
                  <author>A. O.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 143 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Fabian ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of an unidentified work in French.</note>
                  <note>Preliminary pages are cropped in the filmed copy. Signature A3-25 photographed from Yale University copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alexander, --  the Great, 356-323 B.C.</term>
               <term>Conspiracies --  Greece.</term>
               <term>Greece --  History --  Macedonian Expansion, 359-323 B.C.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SCHOOL FOR PRINCES.</p>
            <p>OR, Political Reflections upon three Conſpiracies preceding the Death of <hi>Alexander the Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of French by</hi> A. O.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>TF</head>
               <figDesc>printers device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Fabian,</hi> at the Bible in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:81"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:81"/>
            <head>Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Preface being no more than a Door giving entrance to a Trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, I ſhall here on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſt follow that Notion, and briefly preſent to view the Subject of the enſuing Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three Conſpiracies preceding the Death of</hi> Alexander the Great, <hi>are here at large repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted;
<pb facs="tcp:62981:82"/> with Political Reflections upon every remarkable Occurrence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The chief of the firſt</hi> Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>is</hi> Philotas, <hi>a Favorite of his</hi> Prince, <hi>and General of the</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry; <hi>his Ambition gives Birth to his Diſloyalty; and</hi> Dymnus (<hi>a</hi> Confederate) <hi>his Affection towards</hi> Nicomachus <hi>(a</hi> Youth <hi>of his Acquaintance) diſcovers him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Author of the ſecond</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy <hi>is</hi> Hermolaus, <hi>a</hi> Youth, <hi>one of the</hi> King's Pages: <hi>The Occaſion, His receiving Blows for killing a</hi> Wild Boar <hi>the</hi> King <hi>was going to encounter with his Spear: His</hi> Deſign <hi>ready to take effect,
<pb facs="tcp:62981:82"/> is ſtrangely prevented by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervening of a</hi> Woman, <hi>inſpir'd with a</hi> Prophetick Spirit, <hi>and totally diſcloſed by</hi> Epimenes <hi>(one of his</hi> Aſſociates) <hi>either out of Fear towards their Gods, or purely for Avarice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third and laſt</hi> Conſpiracy <hi>is promoted by</hi> Antipater, <hi>for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the instances of</hi> Olympias <hi>(the King's Mother) removed from his</hi> Government <hi>of</hi> Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>None are ingaged in this</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy <hi>but</hi> Antipater <hi>and his three Sons,</hi> Caſſander, Jollas, <hi>and</hi> Philip: <hi>And</hi> Jollas, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander'<hi>s chief Cup-bearer, taking the opportunity of a Feaſt at</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,
<pb facs="tcp:62981:83"/> 
               <hi>poiſons</hi> Hercules <hi>his Cup; of which</hi> Alexander <hi>drinks, and in a miſerable manner breaths out the remaining minutes of his Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. O.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62981:83"/>
            <head>A SCHOOL FOR PRINCES.</head>
            <p>HE that writes the Life and Death of Princes, may be liken'd to a Painter that has drawn a Picture ſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, repreſenting two ſeveral things, according as it is view'd on either ſide. The Life of great Ones conſider'd on the one ſide by Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, appears to them full of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and a Happineſs not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd. On the other ſide, Politicians admire in it Soveraign Power, and laughing at thoſe falſe Sages that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62981:84"/> never knew the worth of it; reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in a Monarch the ineſtimable Act of ruling Men. So likewiſe at the death of a Prince, the Cynique exagerates the vanity of great Ones; but the true Sage contemplates their End as the Limits of Glory, and the birth of a new Grandeur.</p>
            <p>'Tis not my deſign to write the Lives of Princes; we read in divers Authors, both Ancient and Modern, all that the moſt expert can imagine upon the Art of Governing. I ſhall only tie my ſelf to the conſideration of divers Events commonly preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, accompanying, or following their Death. Hiſtory is like a Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, on which is repreſented the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of Fortune, there ſhall we find Subjects Paricides of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, and Soveraigns precipitating themſelves from a Throne, to an Abyſs of Miſery. Sometimes there's more Bloodſhed at the death of Kings than Tears; their Funerals are diſturb'd by the noiſe of Trumpets,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62981:84"/> and the claſhing of glittering Arms, diſſipates in a moment the cloudy preparations of a Funeral-pomp; ſo that the memory of him, whom but a little before, invironed with Glory and Majeſty, every one ador'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes then an abomination.</p>
            <p>It may not therefore be unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to draw this two-ſided Portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; Policy and Morality ſhall work together; the latter, auſtere and rough, ſhall cover the Heavens with Clouds, and dart down Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts on the Heads of Princes; the former, more clear and dextrous, ſhall avert the Storm, and ſhew them a Sanctuary: So that when one ſhall frighten a Prince with an imminent Danger, the other ſhall preſently give him the Hand; and it ſhall be eaſy for him to avoid the Danger, if he make but good uſe of Political Precepts.</p>
            <p>All that we can imagine moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in Policy, the ſubtileſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes upon the Art of Governing,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62981:85"/> the acuteſt Precepts, cannot make an Impreſſion ſtrong enough upon the Spirit; an example of what is paſt, prevails upon it farther than the fear of what's to come; Experience perſwades with greater eaſe than me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation; and we are more inclin'd to imitate great Actions that have bin already executed, than to be the firſt Enterpriſers of them; the Event is not at all fear'd, where others have bin proſperous; but where they have bin ſucceſsleſs, there the Sage avoids falling into the ſame misfortune.</p>
            <p>'Tis for this Reaſon I have choſen for the Subject of my Work the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of a Prince, whom Fortune, Merit, and Reputation, have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd above all others, and whoſe Actions ought to be of more Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: Never was there Prince more happy all his Life, nor more conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favoured by Fortune; but after he had finiſh'd his courſe, he might be reckon'd the unhappieſt of all Princes, if there be after Death
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62981:85"/> any ſentiment of earthly things.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great. Kings ought to imitate his Vertues, which none more eminently poſſeſs'd; and at the ſame time abominate the Vices he plung'd himſelf into, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to his Rank, or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration for the eſteem of Men. The Diſcreet will admire his judicious and clear Conduct, and cannot but be tranſported at the irregularity of his Manners. Never was there any had a better Birth, greater Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, or truer Merit; nor was there ever any with ſuch notorious Vices ſo contrary to ſuch a Merit, Birth and Grandeur. Was there ever ſeen a Prince more glorious, more admir'd by Strangers; or more often outrag'd by his Friends, in whom he moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fided. When Fortune made him Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Univerſe, hardly could he ſecure himſelf from Domeſtick Treaſons; 'tis true, he ran headlong to his own ruin, and I find not in any Hiſtory, an example of ſuch He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62981:86"/> Virtue, and ſuch a proſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all ſorts of Vices. If then the remembrance of a Recompence is capable to engage the Spirit of a Man to perform Actions full of Virtue and Glory; and if a ſight of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries that accompany Vice can frighten and deter, without doubt there's no Hiſtory more clear than this, to direct Princes in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Death was preceeded by three Conſpiracies, accompanied with a jealouſy for Superiority among his Captains, and follow'd with the ruin of that great Empire. The different Events that compoſe this Hiſtory, the general Deſolation of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Kingdoms, the malignity of Fortune, and the unexpected diſmal Accidents, will furniſh Princes with moſt neceſſary Precepts, both Moral and Politick; and though it may ſeem that all things are abſolutely ſubject to the Order of Fate, yet 'tis very much for a Monarch's Glory
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62981:86"/> when the Revolution of his States cannot be imputed unto him, but only to that fatal and inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that the prudence of Man cannot alter. As for the reſt, though the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> and all thoſe other Nations conquer'd by <hi>Alexander,</hi> had Laws and Cuſtoms quite different from ours, they excell'd in the Art of Government. Policy is from all Ages.</p>
            <p>I come therefore now to examine, in this Conqueror's Conduct, all that's moſt remarkable, that Princes may form themſelves according to ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Model. The Actions of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the Intreigues of the Conſpirators, will teach them to defend themſelves from Domeſtick Treaſons, and to elevate themſelves by Juſtice, Clemency, and Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as much above the Vulgar, as they exceed them in Grandeur, and the advantages of Birth. I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Conſpiracy of <hi>Philotas,</hi> ſo much the more blameable, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62981:87"/> the Death of his Maſter, and his King, as he was indebted to him for his Fortune.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62981:87"/>
               <head>THE CONSPIRACY OF <hi>PHILOTAS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALexander</hi> was arriv'd to the higheſt pitch of Grandeur; <hi>Darius</hi> was dead, and his Army van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd; <hi>Aſia</hi> had chang'd her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who ſeeing himſelf in the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Throne, and finding nothing more on Earth to ſatisfy his Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would have had his Subjects gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him Divine Worſhip. The lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of too great Majeſty, is ſo far from attracting Reſpect and Fear, that it excites great Ones to Envy, and makes them aſpire to wear the Diadem; and whoſoever equals himſelf to the Gods, is unworthy to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62981:88"/> live among Men. And hence it came that <hi>Philotas,</hi> one in <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Army, that could not ſupport his Pride, endeavoured to diſpatch him.</p>
               <p>Of all Vices, Ambition is the moſt dangerous, becauſe it bears a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of Virtue; it has apparently the ſame end; the deſire of Glory is inſeparable to them both; and of this <hi>Philotas</hi> was as greedy as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</hi> Virtue and Ambition have their original from the ſame Source, from grandeur of Courage, from a noble, bold, and undertaking Spirit; the difference I find between them is this, Juſtice limits bounds to Virtue; Ambition knows none, has no Faith, no Friendſhip, no Honeſty: it dares all things; neither the fear of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, nor the power of Juſtice can detain it: it generates thoſe criminal thoughts that ſtrike at Royalty, the hatred, jealouſie, and revenge of great Ones.</p>
               <p>Three ſorts of Perſons commonly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62981:88"/> conſpire the Death of Princes. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain melancholy People, who at any price whatſoever, though it be at the expence of their Lives, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe extraordinary Actions to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe their Memory to Poſterity, not much caring whether it be honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or held in abomination; ſuch was he that burnt the Temple of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana;</hi> the <hi>Jacobin</hi> that kill'd <hi>Henry</hi> III, and many others. Some tranſported with an abominable deſire of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, care not to ſurvive an Injury receiv'd, as he that ſtab'd <hi>Henry</hi> IV. And almoſt all great Ones, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of a State, hope for ſome change of Fortune.</p>
               <p>For this laſt reaſon the common People are to be feared, when a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is changed from a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy to a Monarchy; the Nobility, when it has bin an Ariſtocracy; the Princes of the Blood, if a Kingdom be Hereditary; the Miniſters and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorites, if Elective.</p>
               <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Macedonia</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62981:89"/> for ſeveral Ages from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Son; and whilſt there were Succeſſors, no one dar'd enterpriſe any thing againſt his King's Life. <hi>Alexander</hi> labour'd to ſecure himſelf immortality by Actions of an Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick Courage, by the grandeur of his Enterprizes; he was enflam'd with a deſire of Glory, little minding the preſervation of his Life, and leſs the leaving a Succeſſor to his Empire. He prefer'd <hi>Bagoas</hi> before <hi>Barſine; Roxane</hi> known to be great with Child at his Death, could not keep the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonian</hi> Captains from dividing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, thoſe vaſt and lovely Provinces, into as many King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. The Scepter of <hi>Alexander</hi> therefore being to fall into ſtrange Hands, his Nobles pretended to his Crown: which there was no appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their arriving to, the King being young and vigorous; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were to haſten their Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations by the means of Ingratitude, of Treachery, of a Crime horrid
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62981:89"/> and deteſtable. Nothing retains Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, but the fear of a lawful Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, in which conſiſts the ſecurity of a Prince; for there's none will form any Deſign contrary to his Faith and Duty, unleſs he be ſupported by more than ordinary hopes. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s Death would have made al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as many Kings as were <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Captains; what wonder then if he were continually expos'd to the murmuring of his Souldiers, to the Infidelity of his Friends, to Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Treacheries?</p>
               <p>I am much miſtaken if it were not this that firſt gave <hi>Philotas</hi> thoughts of advancing himſelf to Royalty: <hi>Parmenios</hi>'s Valour, Merit, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, who commanded a puiſſant Army in <hi>Media,</hi> confirm'd him in his Deſign, and his own Grandeur finiſh'd his Reſolve.</p>
               <p>'Tis dangerous to ſuffer any to approach too near to that whoſe Poſſeſſion can make them happy; that Huſband may blame himſelf,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62981:90"/> that ſhews his Wife to another, who after falls in love with her. Royalty has greater Charms; 'tis like a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd Glaſs, dull'd with the leaſt Breath of thoſe are near it; or like the Fountain of <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent Beauty appearing in it is ſo charming, that there's none can ſee it, and live without the enjoyment. A Prince that gives too great prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a Favorite, a Miniſter, or a great Captain, nouriſhes a Rival, a cruel Enemy, a Competitor for his Empire; that has but one ſtep to mount into his Throne. We read in the Hiſtories of all Ages, of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kings Favorites, of an obſcure Birth, incapable of great Matters, who coming into an entire poſſeſſion of their Maſter's Favours, oftentimes, by ways ſhameful and wicked, have dar'd to aſpire to their Crowns. What may we not then expect from a great Captain, Generous, Liberal, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, of an illuſtrious Birth, Head of a powerful Army, belov'd of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62981:90"/> the Souldiers, and the common Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</p>
               <p>I own it pleaſant for a Monarch to diſcharge himſelf of the weighty Burthen of State-Affairs, on the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of ſome Miniſter; to repoſe himſelf from the Glory of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, upon the valour of a great Captain; to intruſt his moſt ſecret Thoughts with the Wiſdom and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of a Favorite: But this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorite, this Miniſter, this Captain ſhould be only Executors, and not Maſters of their Prince's Will; and this Prince ſhould as far exceed them in diſcerning Merit, in underſtanding of Affairs, in judicious Fore-ſight, in eminency of Capacity, as in Power and Grandeur. Such exquiſite Parts are to be feared in a Favorite, his Fidelity is ſhaken by ſo great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and we have ſeen in this Age a King, formidable to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, implore the Aſſiſtance of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King againſt his Favorite. If a Prince muſt needs ſpend his Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62981:91"/> if he muſt needs heap up Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours upon his Subjects, let him take heed not to beſtow them all in one Place, or on ſeveral Perſons united in Friendſhip or Blood, who may have the ſame Deſires, the ſame Will.</p>
               <p>Be a Miniſter never ſo powerful, if he have but one Employ, one Charge in an Empire, he can have no more Creatures than his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty reaches: Should he meditate any Deſign deſtructive to the State, he would meet with a thouſand Obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. A General of an Army, who is neither Maſter of the Treaſury, nor has Intelligence with a Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendent, is not at all to be feared: He that commands the Land-Forces is oppos'd to the Admiral, the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the People to the Souldier's Rebellion; but if a Miniſter be Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of an Army, Superintendent of the Treaſury, Admiral; or if theſe Charges are at his diſpoſal, what is there that he cannot do? if faithful, he is formidable; if unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, he is King.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62981:91"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parmenio</hi> and <hi>Philotas</hi> were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Empire, one General of the Cavalry, the other of a whole Army; the former Governor of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Provinces, Superintendent of the Treaſury, having in all Battels the command of one Wing; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter awing the great Ones, a Favorite, and Arbiter of his Prince's Life. The immenſe Riches of <hi>Philotas,</hi> the great number of Creatures of all ſorts and conditions inſeparably lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to his Fortune; his Authority in the Armies almoſt equalling the King's, might well induce him young as he was, cruel, full of delicacy and pride, to conſpire the death of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> the only Let to him in his way to the higheſt pitch of Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur. Add to theſe the Love of a Woman, the true cauſe of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antigone,</hi> of a noble Birth; an excellent Beauty; a ſweet Nature; a lively, pleaſant, charming Spirit; was one of thoſe illuſtrious Priſoners
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62981:92"/> that the Governor of <hi>Damaſcus</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to <hi>Permenio,</hi> with all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures <hi>Darius</hi> had committed to his diſloyal cuſtody. This fair Slave made her ſelf Miſtreſs of <hi>Philotas</hi> his Liberty; he forgot that he had all power over her, and ſhamefully ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf to her Laws. That pride, that contempt, that made him but a little before deſpiſe <hi>Darius</hi> his Nobles, the chiefeſt of the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and equal himſelf to his King, chang'd it ſelf immediately into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to his own Captive; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came fearful, (as are the greateſt part of Lovers) and thought himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of her, becauſe he was not <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The violence of his Paſſion, rouzes in his Heart a vehement deſire of making himſelf King: impatient of enjoying <hi>Antigone,</hi> he deſpairs of poſſeſſing her, unleſs he ſhare the Empire with her. At the Wars, egg'd on with great Love and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he expoſes himſelf to dangers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62981:92"/> more than ordinary; he is liberal to prodigality, gentle, affable, gains the Hearts of his Souldiers, cloaths himſelf like them, accommodates himſelf to their Manners, protects them, is belov'd, and reigns already over the whole Army. But ſo many good Qualities were produc'd by Love, which being blind, can never guide Lovers in their Conduct; and in his, Reaſon and Prudence had no ſhare.</p>
               <p>At Table, in his Bed, in the midſt of good Cheer and Imbracements, he begins to celebrate his Actions. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> could not recompence them with a Kingdom large enough, for his Ambition. <hi>Philotas</hi> looks on him no longer as his Benefactor; accuſes him of Injuſtice; ſpeaks inſolently of him; debaſes this great Monarch; aſcribes all his Conqueſts to <hi>Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio;</hi> lets ſcape ſome injurious Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: the moſt clear-ſighted pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into his Deſigns, and ſuſpect his Loyalty.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62981:93"/>
               <p>Perhaps he might think that he diſcharg'd his Heart into the Boſom of a Woman amorous and diſcreet. A ſtrange thing; that ſo many Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Infidelity cannot make Lovers ſuſpicious of the uſual Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of their Miſtreſſes. Fickle <hi>Antigone</hi> ceaſes to love <hi>Philotas,</hi> and betrays him. She muſt deſtroy him to preſerve her new Lover; She thinks it her ſecureſt way to acquaint <hi>Alexander</hi> with the imminent danger threatning him. <hi>Craterus,</hi> whom the King honour'd particularly with his Favour, jealous of <hi>Philotas</hi> his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and an Enemy to his Grandeur, ſeeks occaſion to ruin him: which <hi>Antigone</hi> proffers him, and tells him all that miſerable Wretch had diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd to her of his Mind, during the moſt tender moments of their privacy.</p>
               <p>As it is impoſſible that the Duſt caſt into the Wind ſhould not be ſcatter'd, ſo it is very difficult for a Secret intruſted with a Woman,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62981:93"/> young, handſom, and amorous, not to be divulg'd. She longs to know that that's kept from her, and when ſhe knows it, deſires as much to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it. She is ardent in her Purſuit, treacherous after Enjoyment, cruel in her new Love. No kindneſs can retain her, the remembrance of a Man ſhe has lov'd tenderly, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morouſly embrac'd, affects her not, like the Earth that darkens the Sun, from whence it receives its warmth. But if there be any thing firm in the tenderneſs of her Sentiments, happy is the Man that has her, ſhe is an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible Sourſe of Pleaſures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Craterus</hi> glad to deſtroy his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, by preſerving the Life of his King, runs to <hi>Alexander,</hi> and gives him an account of what he had heard. <hi>Antigone</hi> is call'd, and is not aſham'd to publiſh her own Infamy, and the ſecret of a Man that ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely lov'd her. The King never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs diſſembles, whether it were that the conſideration of <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62981:94"/> great Services, his unbyaſs'd Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, his incorrupted Loyalty, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd him to Clemency; or whether it were that he thought <hi>Philotas</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, or feared too lightly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, upon the bare teſtimony of a <hi>ſlave,</hi> the fidelity of an ancient Servant, moſt paſſionate for his Glory, one of his chief Captains and Confidents, adored by the Souldiers for his Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and Magnificence. But For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that took a particular care of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and prepar'd for him new Conqueſts, diſcover'd the whole In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treigue of a moſt horrid Plot. <hi>Dym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> one in no great Authority at Court, but of a ſtout Heart, and great Spirit, was one of thoſe that had conſpir'd the King's Death; he was ſo in love with a young Youth call'd <hi>Nicomachus,</hi> that he could not but intruſt him with a Secret, upon which depended his own ſafety; and that of ſo many Perſons of Quality who were concern'd in the Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize. He declares it to him, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62981:94"/> endeavours to perſwade him to make one, as well from the conſideration of their Friendſhip, as from that of his future Grandeur after the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. He Weeps, Careſſes, Threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, Urges, and ſometimes promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him a Kingdom; ſometimes ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Image of Death before his Eyes, if he refuſe to hold with them; <hi>Would'st thou have</hi> (ſays he) <hi>my dear</hi> Nichomachus, <hi>a greater Teſtimony of my Affection? I truſt my Life to thy Faith, and I call thee to be a ſharer in the Empire of all</hi> Aſia.</p>
               <p>This young Youth bearing a great love towards his King, was ſeized with horror at a Crime ſo full of cruelty; he proteſts he'l never be wanting to his Duty, to the Loyalty he owes his Maſter; that all he can do for his Friend, is not to ruin him, if he'l repent of ſo great a wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dymnus</hi> ſtood wavering between Love and Fear; at length ſetting his Sword at his Friend's Breſt, calling
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62981:95"/> him ſometimes Coward, ſometimes Traitor, he was going to begin with him the execution of his Deſign, but that the young Man in a fright pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd more than he was ask'd. He feigned therefore a reſolution to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Enterprize, and deſired to know the number and quality of the Conſpirators. <hi>Dymnus,</hi> full of joy that he had gain'd him, names <hi>Peu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colaus, Nicanor, Aphaebetus, Loceus, Demetrius, Dioxenus, Archepolis</hi> and <hi>Amyntas.</hi> 'Tis certain he made no mention of <hi>Philotas,</hi> who, I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to think, according to the cuſtom of great Ones, lay expecting the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of the Conſpiracy, and left others to carry it on, that if it were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd, he might caſt the whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign on them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicomachus</hi> tranſported with joy, that it lay in his power to ſhew his King a proof of his Fidelity, runs to his Brother <hi>Ceballinus,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints him with the whole Matter. 'Tis a wonder that the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62981:95"/> mention'd in Hiſtory, have bin always diſcover'd by the moſt wicked of thoſe that have enterpriz'd them. Intemperance of ſpeech is the inſeparable Companion of Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, and incompatible with Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which chiefly conſiſts in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all, in diſtruſting even Reaſon it ſelf, and in keeping ſilence.</p>
               <p>It was not convenient for <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus</hi> to go to the King in Perſon, the Conſpirators might have ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Fidelity; they doubted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>Ceballinus,</hi> who was uſually in the Palace: And he not loſing a minute of time, endeavour'd to ſpeak with <hi>Alexander.</hi> At firſt there was none to introduce him, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards there appear'd <hi>Philotas,</hi> to whom in a great fright he relates what he had heard of the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and prays him to advertiſe the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philotas</hi> his ſilence, is for certain a moſt convincing proof of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty. He is not troubled at this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62981:21"/> Relation, the danger he ſees himſelf expos'd to concerns him not, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his own preſervation cannot abate his Courage, fierce and cruel towards himſelf: he praiſes <hi>Ceballinus</hi> his Loyalty, and is himſelf diſloyal; he returns again to the King (for he could not well do otherwiſe without giving ſuſpicion) but diſcourſes with him all the while of other Matters.</p>
               <p>The Night came on, <hi>Ceballinus</hi> wondered there was no ſtir made, the King being in ſo imminent danger; and meeting with <hi>Philotas,</hi> asked him if he had inform'd <hi>Alexander</hi> of what he had told him? His anſwer was, That he had not the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Ceballinus</hi> grew more miſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, when he ſaw the Conſpirators the next day walking freely in the Palace, <hi>Alexander</hi> having done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to them, ſuitable to the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his reſentment ſhould have made him take: and addreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf again to <hi>Philotas,</hi> he intreated him not to neglect an Affair of that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62981:21"/> Conſequence, that concern'd the King's Life. He anſwered him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, He would be mindful of it.</p>
               <p>Several Hiſtorians have thought <hi>Philotas</hi> innocent; becauſe, ſay they, there's no likelihood that a Man of his Courage and Reputation, ſhould have bin two days without provide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his ſafety, either by diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ceballinus</hi> and his Brother, or by an ingenuous acknowledgment of his perfidious Crime. <hi>Plutarch,</hi> a great ſtickler for the Glory of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> endeavours to juſtify him; but that Learned Man, as innocent as he makes <hi>Philotas,</hi> did not well conſider, that his ſilence could not but be eſteem'd a Crime, in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all Politicians. 'Twas for his ſecurity to hold his peace; in ſpeaking there was danger, either of loſing his Life, or his Reputation. It may be the King might have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd him: Can a Man of Spirit ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive an Infamy? His Authority might have ſhelter'd him from the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62981:22"/> ſtorm, and have made the cloud break over others heads. What likelihood? Do thoſe that are drawn to Execution, fear after Death the diſgrace of great Ones? What then? tell the Conſpirators that their Plot was diſcover'd? He, who was the Head of the Conſpiracy, cared not to frighten thoſe that were to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute it. There's no Reſolution but ſtaggers at the fear of Puniſhment; Conſtancy ſhakes at the apprehenſion of being call'd in queſtion; there muſt be then a recourſe to new Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, <hi>Philotas</hi> muſt rather animate his Confederates, than terrify them: What if he had made away with <hi>Ceballinus</hi> in the King's Palace, in the Camp, in the very Arms of his Companions, what would <hi>Nicoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> have ſaid, whom 'twas impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to find as he had hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? All theſe Precautions were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive. <hi>Philotas</hi> did like a great Politician, to ſay nothing to the King, to ſay nothing to the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62981:22"/> and to make no noiſe. He entertain'd <hi>Ceballinus</hi> with fair words, the day for the Enterpriſe was come, and according to all appearance <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballinus</hi> ſhou'd have rely'd on the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity of <hi>Philotas,</hi> a Favorite of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s, and one who had greater Intereſt than any in his preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Ceballinus</hi> not believing that the King wou'd ſlight his Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, began to be miſtruſtful. He goes to <hi>Metron,</hi> a young Gentleman that kept the King's Wardrobe, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the Enterpriſe to him: who preſently cauſing him to be hid, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints the King with it as he was bathing himſelf. <hi>Alexander</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gives order to apprehend <hi>Dymnus;</hi> he enters his Wardrobe, <hi>Ceballinus</hi> cries out, I ſee, Sir, you are deliver'd from the hands of Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
               <p>The King afterwards enquiring touching the Circumſtances of the Conſpiracy, he told him every thing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62981:23"/> that <hi>Dymnus</hi> had declar'd. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving confeſs'd that it was three days ſince his Brother gave him notice, <hi>Alexander</hi> doubted not but that he was one of the Confederates, ſince he had ſo long defer'd his Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And therefore he caus'd him preſently to be ſhackl'd. <hi>Ceballinus,</hi> who expected a recompence for his fidelity; feeling the weight of his Chains, cries out in an aſtoniſhment, That the very firſt moment he knew of the Conſpiracy, he ran and gave notice of it to <hi>Philotas,</hi> the only cauſe of this delay.</p>
               <p>Then <hi>Alexander,</hi> pierced with grief to ſee himſelf ſo baſely betray'd by a Man loaded with his Favours, and ſo particularly honour'd with his Friendſhip, lifted up his hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven; and, as it were, ſeiz'd with horror, deteſted with Tears ſo hideous an Ingratitude.</p>
               <p>Without doubt there's no Grief equals that of having paſſionately lov'd one that proves ingrateful and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62981:23"/> perfidious. When we call to mind, that after all the pains we have taken, after all the proofs we have given of a true Affection and great Truſt, we are paid with Ingratitude, we can blame none but our ſelves, we muſt condemn our own Judgments. One would think Nature declares her ſelf againſt us, ſince ſhe has indu'd the meaneſt Plant with acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſeems to rob us of it. This example of Ingratitude will teach an honeſt Man not to expect returns from a Perſon he obliges. Favours ſhould only proceed from our incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to do good; the Heart of a Man's the more noble the leſs 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed, and the pleaſure of venting his Generoſity, is to the honeſt Man recompence enough.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dymnus</hi> ſeeing himſelf inviron'd with Guards, troubled at the enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of his Crime, and the Image of a Death, accompanied with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pains, ran himſelf through with his own Sword, and would have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62981:24"/> made an end of himſelf upon the Spot, had not the Souldiers inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted him.</p>
               <p>To kill ones ſelf, is in my opinion the baſeſt and the unworthieſt of all Actions. Let Antiquity drain its Eloquence, to praiſe the reſolution of <hi>Cato</hi> or <hi>Lucretia;</hi> as for me, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but blame Antiquity for calling Cowardiſe, Valour; Folly, Wiſdom; Deſpair, Virtue. He has no Heart that kills himſelf, becauſe he will not ſurvive a misfortune more terrible than Death. I call Grandeur of Courage, that conſtancy with which the wiſe Man boldly expects the laſt moment of his Life, as the end of all things, not of miſery. For then Death's a favour, it ſets at liberty, and makes thoſe happy, that are ſwept from a dark train of Miſeries accompanying Life. <hi>Cato</hi> could die, but he could not ſupport <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred. His Misfortunes caſt him into deſpair, becauſe his Wiſdom aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd him in his Misfortunes. The
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62981:24"/> deſire of Life is more vehement than any; to vanquiſh this may ſeem a compleat Victory; true Wiſdom, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Government over the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but in reality, 'tis Fear that is victorious, occaſion'd by ſome preſent diſlike, ſight of Torments, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of worſe to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dymnus</hi> thus wounded, was drag'd to the Palace, <hi>Alexander,</hi> as ſoon as he ſaw him, <hi>How comes it Vilain</hi> (ſays he in a paſſion) <hi>that thou haſt judged</hi> Philotas <hi>more worthy of the Empire of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe than me?</hi> This miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wretch was already ſpeechleſs, and turning his Face from the King's, he fetch'd a deep ſigh (a proof as it were of his Crime) and yielded up the Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>'Tis a weakneſs to ſhow any ſigns of Repentance. A Man that is any thing dextrous, though he be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, accus'd, condemn'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62981:25"/> him. <hi>Dymnus</hi> preſs'd with remorſe of Conſcience, is troubled, ſtabs himſelf, ſighs, and becomes his own Accuſer, Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Executioner. Could he have expected a greater Puniſhment? Why then not indure the Face of <hi>Alexander?</hi> Why then avouch his Perfidy, and declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Vilain?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ceballinus</hi> could not have deſir'd a greater proof as to the truth of what he had ſaid; and <hi>Philotas</hi> juſtify'd him to his own condemnation, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him from his Chains to put them on himſelf. The King, who whilſt <hi>Philotas</hi> was abſent, had complain'd of his Ingratitude with tears, could not diſſemble his reſentment when he ſaw him. Wherefore with anger in his looks he ſpake thus; <q>
                     <hi>Ceballinus</hi> deſerves extream puniſhment, if he has bin three days without making me acquainted with a Conſpiracy againſt my Perſon; but if he gave you information as ſoon as ever he knew it, your ſilence is yet more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62981:25"/> inexcuſable, conſidering the great Teſtimonies of my Truſt and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. I cannot imagine what ſhould induce you to ſo horrid a Treaſon. I have yet ſome ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Affection for you; If you are innocent, <hi>Ceballinus</hi> deſerves to die; if guilty, make an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous confeſſion, I am not inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It concerns the prudence of a Criminal to be throughly acquainted with the quality of his Crime, and not to confeſs it, if of ſo heinous a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as to exceed his Prince's Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency. An ingenuous acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Fault, committed through a deſire of Revenge, or by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigation of Choler or Envy, may meet with favour; but for Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Diſloyalty in a Favorite, there's no hopes of Pardon.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs <hi>Philotas</hi> ingenuouſly confeſſes that <hi>Ceballinus</hi> inform'd him two days ſince that <hi>Alexander</hi> was in danger of his Life, and that he told
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62981:26"/> him the whole order of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy. <q>But what likelihood, ſaid he, that I ſhould give credit to the relation of an infamous Perſon, and in reporting it to the King, expoſe my ſelf to the laughter of the whole Court? <hi>He added,</hi> That if the thing had bin found falſe, he ſhould have ſacrificed himſelf to the hatred of thoſe Nobles nam'd among the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators: that nevertheleſs <hi>Dymnus</hi>'s Death did ſufficiently declare what he had thought fitteſt to conceal. And then imbracing the King's knees, he humbly beſought him to pardon a Man he had ſo much lov'd, and who had hitherto given a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand proofs of an untainted Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; ſince the only Crime that could be imputed to him, was, that he had neglected an Information, that he could not believe true.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As for me, I am ready to think, that if <hi>Philotas</hi> had diſown'd his Fault, the King would never have ſuſpected the fidelity of ſuch a Friend,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62981:26"/> upon the bare Teſtimony of a young debauch'd Youth. The Grandeur of his Services, the Merit of <hi>Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio,</hi> his Birth, <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Affection, Eſteem, and Fortune, which made him think himſelf beyond the reach of Ambuſhes, would have pleaded his Cauſe. <hi>Dymnus</hi> was dead, <hi>Cebal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> had given him his Information in private; What had this unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Man to fear, but the remorſe of his Conſcience, which compel'd him to confeſs his Fault? Such force has Guilt to blind the Guilty.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Philotas</hi> was free and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo <hi>Alexander</hi> was cloſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit. He gave him the Hand, ſeeming to believe him, and ſtay'd him to ſup with him, with ſuch ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and freedom, that <hi>Philotas,</hi> aſſured of his Reconciliation, thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf more in favour with his Prince than ever. But he was not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Heart of Man, Fortune makes it as changeable as <hi>Proteus;</hi> the Manners and Cuſtoms
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62981:27"/> of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> a new Grandeur, the Empire of the Univerſe had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd for the worſe a diſpoſition for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſweet, gentle, and inclin'd to Good more than any; and <hi>Philotas</hi> ſhould have bin perſwaded, by the alteration Ambition had made in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that when Fortune ſmiles, we are like her, inconſtant, diſloyal, and quite a different thing from what we appear to be. The Wine, and good Cheer warm'd <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Revenge. The Feaſt was no ſooner ended, but he call'd a Council of his Friends; who having heard the Relation of <hi>Nicomachus,</hi> and the King's Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereupon, judged <hi>Philotas</hi> his deſtruction as good, as reſolv'd upon. <hi>Craterus,</hi> his Enemy, and one of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Favorites, lays hold on this Occaſion to exerciſe his particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Vengeance, under pretext of zeal and love for his Maſter; ſays he,</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Sir, Why did not you acquaint us preſently with <hi>Philotas</hi> his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity?
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62981:27"/> We would have counſel'd you to have pardon'd this Traytor, without ſhewing him that he was indebted to you for his Life. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an attempt upon yours, and a Pardon for that moſt abominable Crime, what will he not dare? What may he not expect from your Clemency? Think not, Sir, that the danger he has ſeen himſelf in, will render him more loyal for the future. It will not be always in your power to prevent this Parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide. He'l obſerve other Meaſures, and lay ſuch Snares, as 'twill be impoſſible for you to eſcape. For fear the leaſt Fault of his ſhould waken your Indignation, he'l en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour again to deprive you of your Life. And though <hi>Philotas</hi> his Heart be intirely chang'd, the news of his Crime, and your Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, will provoke <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s. Will he, in the Authority he is in, loaded with Honour and Glory, at the Head of a great Army, be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62981:28"/> to acknowledg that he has any Obligation to you for his Son's Life? Some Favours are look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Injuries. Without doubt he'l accuſe you of Ingratitude and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and will rather take away your Life, than have it thought that <hi>Philotas</hi> has deſerv'd Death. Pray, Sir, conſider the imminent danger you are threatned with; We have done our Duty, there's none can impute your Deſtruction to us, after the counſel we have given you to provide for your Safety.</q>
               </p>
               <p>There's no Eloquence more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſive, than that of a Courtier; He's a vehement and pathetick Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, who knows his Prince's Genius, his Weakneſs, his Inclination, the Intriegues of the Court and all its Policies. <hi>Craterus</hi> his Speech, though artificial, appeared full of Zeal, and prevail'd in Council. You ſee how cunningly he could conceal under a profound diſſimulation, the jealouſy he had a long time had of <hi>Philotas</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:62981:28"/> his Grandeur. Of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, there was not one that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took this miſerable Man's defence; all concluded upon his Death.</p>
               <p>The reſolution they had taken re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd ſecrecy; which <hi>Alexander</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to them; and to avoid giving ſuſpicion, he order'd all his Captains to get ready to march on the morrow. In the mean while <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Erigyus, Leonatus</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diccas,</hi> received order to ſend out a detachment of Cavalry, to ſeize all the Paſſages that led into <hi>Media,</hi> that <hi>Parmenio</hi> might have no intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence given him. And about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night <hi>Attarras</hi> commanding three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hundred Men, went out to ſecure <hi>Philotas</hi> his Houſe. Fifty of the boldeſt of them forc'd the Dore; and whether it were that he rely'd on his reconciliation with the King, or that his Diſquiets had over-tired his Spirits, <hi>Attarras</hi> loaded him with Irons whilſt he lay faſt a-ſleep. The ruſtling of Arms, and the weight of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62981:29"/> his Chains wakening him at the ſame time, he cry'd out, ſtarting; <hi>Ah! Sir, the malice of my Enemies has prevail'd with your bounty.</hi> They carried him afterwards to the Palace, neither his Fetters, nor the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Miſery, being able to extract from him ſo much as one word, or one groan.</p>
               <p>The Authority of the Kings of <hi>Macedonia</hi> was limited, during Peace by the common People, and in time of War by the Souldery; both the one and the other were Judges of Capital Crimes; ſo that <hi>Alexander,</hi> Emperor as he was, and Maſter of all the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> was forced by the Laws to plead his own Cauſe, and be the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer of <hi>Philotas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> having caus'd the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians</hi> to be aſſembled in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and expos'd the Body of <hi>Dym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> to their view, ſpake to them in manner following: <q>Souldiers, a handful of Conſpirators had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rob'd you of <hi>Alexander.</hi> I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62981:29"/> owe my ſafety to the Gods. I have liv'd to ſee you; and your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence animates me the more againſt my Parricides. I cannot bear it, that theſe wicked Vilains would have fruſtrated me of my Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the Fruit of my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, which can be no other than to honour your Valour, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence your Services. Here his</q> Speech was interrupted by the ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Souldiers, who all wept bitterly; from whence he took oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to proſecute in theſe terms. <q>How will you behave your ſelves then, when I ſhew you who theſe Traitors are? I ſcarce dare yet name them, I expel them as far as I am able from my memory, as if this could ſave them from their Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But I muſt ſtifle the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of former friendſhip, and diſcover this abominable Plot. And how indeed can I well conceal it? <hi>Parmenio,</hi> our Friend of a longer ſtanding than any, on whom both
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62981:30"/> my Father and I have liberally heap'd up Favours, has, in his old Age, made himſelf the Head of this Attempt. <hi>Philotas</hi> his Son, the chief Inſtrument of his Treachery, has ſuborn'd <hi>Peucolaus, Demetrius,</hi> this wretched <hi>Dymnus</hi> whoſe Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy lies before you, and as many others as he could find capable of ſo great a madneſs. At theſe words</q> aroſe a great noiſe, and confus'd murmur, ſuch as is common to great Aſſemblies, eſpecially of Souldiers ſeized with anger and amazement. <hi>Nicomachus, Metron,</hi> and <hi>Ceballinus</hi> are introduced. Each of them gives in what he had already declar'd; but none charges <hi>Philotas.</hi> So that the whole Army, hearing no Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt him, immediately laid aſide their Anger, and there was a general ſilence. The King purſu'd thus: <q>What can you imagine the Deſign of a Man, who inform'd of this Conſpiracy, kept it ſecret? <hi>Dymnus</hi> by killing himſelf declar'd
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62981:30"/> the Information true. <hi>Ceballinus</hi> choſe rather to expoſe himſelf to Tortures, than to conceal a thing of ſuch Importance, though he was not certain of it. <hi>Metron</hi> was ſo diſquieted, that to diſcharge himſelf ſoon enough, he ruſh'd into the Chamber where I was bathing. Only <hi>Philotas</hi> believes nothing, fears nothing. A moſt excellent Courage! when his King's in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt danger, he changes not his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance! he ſlights the Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Ah! doubtleſs this ſilence was not without Deſign. The deſire of reigning animated <hi>Philotas</hi> to the perpetration of the higheſt Crime. His Father commands all <hi>Media,</hi> and he relying on the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit he has in my Army, and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining himſelf Maſter of my For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, aſpires to more than he is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, to more than he deſerves. It may be he deſpiſes me becauſe I have no Children; but he's miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, you are my Family; as long as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62981:31"/> you live, I am not without Children.</q> Then he rehears'd the Letter that had bin intercepted, written from <hi>Parmenio</hi> to his two Sons <hi>Nicanor</hi> and <hi>Philotas.</hi> There was nothing charg'd them more home of ſo capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal an Enterpriſe. The ſubſtance of it was this; <q>In the firſt place take care of your ſelves, then of thoſe that are under you, and we need not fear accompliſhing our Deſigns.</q> The King added, <q>That 'twas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in theſe terms, for fear of being intercepted, that none but the Confederates might underſtand it. But you'l ſay, <hi>Dymnus,</hi> when he told <hi>Nicomachus</hi> the Names of the Conſpirators, ſaid nothing of <hi>Philotas.</hi> That's nothing at all, Souldiers, to his Innocency, but rather an effect of his Power. He is ſo dreaded by thoſe that can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him, that when they confeſs their own Crime, they conceal his. We may judg of <hi>Philotas</hi> by the Actions of his Life. He was a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federate
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62981:31"/> in the Conſpiracy of my Couſin <hi>Amyntas</hi> in <hi>Macedonia.</hi> He gave his Siſter in Marriage to <hi>Atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the greateſt of my Enemies. And when I wrote to him in a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Letter, what the Oracle of <hi>Jupiter Ammon</hi> had ſpoken in my favour, he had the confidence to anſwer me, That he was glad to hear I was received into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Gods; but that he pity'd thoſe that were to live under the Government of a Man that could not contain himſelf within the bounds of Humane Nature. Are not theſe ſufficient Marks of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienation of his Spirit, and of the envy he had for my Glory? All this I kept to my ſelf as long as poſſibly I could. For I look'd on it as a ripping up of my own Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, to diſgrace thoſe to whom I had bin ſo favourable. But now they are not Words that are to be chaſtiſed. From liberty of Speech, he has proceeded to that of Action,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62981:32"/> from wounds of Words, to thoſe of Swords. <hi>Philotas</hi> (you may believe it) has deſign'd to aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate me; and if he be capable to perform it, Souldiers, Where ſhall I ſeek for ſafety? Whom ſhall I truſt my Life with? I have made him the only General of the Cavalry, which compoſes the greateſt part of the Army, and the Flower of the young <hi>Macedonian</hi> Nobility. I have committed to his truſt my Safety, Hopes, and Victories. I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd his Father to the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greee you advanc'd me: I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him the Government of <hi>Media,</hi> the Richeſt of our Provinces, with an abſolute command over thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of our Citizens and Allies. In fine, thoſe from whom I expected moſt defence, have bin the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt to ruin me. Far better is it to fall at the Head of an Army by valiant Enemies, than to be butcher'd in a Camp by treacherous Subjects. Preſerv'd from Perils, I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62981:32"/> had reaſon to be afraid of, I am now fallen into thoſe I never fear'd. Souldiers, you have oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd me to have a care of my Life; have a care of it now your ſelves. I put my ſelf into your hands, I have recourſe to your Arms; I will not live except you deſire it, which if you do, ſhew it in avenging me.</q> Then <hi>Philotas</hi> was introduc'd in Chains, his Head cover'd with an old Cloth. 'Twas obſerv'd he was in that condition look'd on with pity, by even thoſe who not long before had envied him. They had ſeen him the day before General of the Cavalry; they knew he Supp'd the ſame Evening with the King, and now they ſaw him at the ſame time Guilty, Condemn'd, and loaded with Chains. They conſider'd likewiſe the ſtrange Fortune of <hi>Parmenio</hi> that great Captain, who lately had loſt two of his Sons, <hi>Hector</hi> and <hi>Nicanor,</hi> and would then ſhortly hear the ſad News of his only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62981:33"/> Son's Condemnation, and of his own Proceſs being made in his abſence. Theſe Reflections made the Aſſembly incline to pity. But <hi>Amyntas</hi> exaſperated them afreſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Philotas;</hi> telling them, <q>That they were betray'd to the <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> that they were in danger of never ſeeing their own Country, their Relations, their Wives; that they were like to be a Body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Head, without Life, without a Name, expos'd in a ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to the deriſion of their Enemies.</q> This Speech, though it prevailed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Philotas,</hi> was not very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the King, who lik'd not that his Souldiers ſhould be diſcourag'd by the remembrance of their Country, and their Wives. <hi>Caenus,</hi> Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in-Law to <hi>Philotas,</hi> inveighed againſt him more violently then any; He call'd him <hi>Traitor to his King, to his Country, to the Army,</hi> and took up a great Stone to throw at his Head, (ſome have thought this was only to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62981:33"/> free him from thoſe Torments that were prepared for him); but the King holding his hand, told him, <hi>That the Priſoner ſhould have liberty to ſpeak for himſelf, and that he would not otherwiſe ſuffer him to be condemn'd. Philotas</hi> therefore is order'd to plead his own Cauſe. But whether it were remorſe of Conſcience, or fear of Death, he dar'd not ſo much as look up, or open his Mouth. He ſhed Tears in abundance, and fainted away in the Arms of him that held him. They wip'd his Eyes, brought him to himſelf, and he was going to ſpeak; which the King perceiving, <hi>The</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians, ſaid he, <hi>ſhall be thy Judges, tell me whether thou intendeſt to uſe the Language of thy own Country?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There are here,</hi> anſwered <hi>Philotas, many that are not</hi> Macedonians, <hi>who will underſtand me better if I uſe the ſame Language you have done;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt on purpoſe to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of moſt.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:62981:34"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Obſerve (ſays <hi>Alexander) Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotas</hi> his arrogance; he diſdains to ſpeak our Language, as if he were aſham'd of being born a <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi> No matter, let him ſpeak how he will; only remember, Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, that our Cuſtoms and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are an abomination to him, thoſe of the Barbarians very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Men are equally inclin'd to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Great, and to pity the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. A ſtrange thing! if you are happy, you are perſecuted by envy; if you are unhappy, you are pitied by every one, but none comforts you. <hi>Caenus,</hi> who had greater Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt than any to preſerve the Honour and Life of <hi>Philotas,</hi> whoſe Siſter he had married, is the firſt that riſes up againſt him; 'tis not enough to call him <hi>Traitor to his King, to his Country, to the Army,</hi> he is the firſt that takes up a Stone to throw at his Head. Many have believ'd that it was then his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to have him ſton'd, that ſo he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62981:34"/> might eſcape more cruel Tortures. But the more expert, who have try'd the Treachery and Inhumanity of the greateſt part of Relations, doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not but that <hi>Caenus</hi> would have ſtifled the Compaſſion <hi>Philotas</hi> his Misfortune had bred in the Hearts of the Souldiers, which taking force through the Grandeur of his Merit, and the power of his Oration, might at laſt cauſe him to be declar'd Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caenus</hi> was one of the Council, when <hi>Philotas</hi> his Death was reſolv'd upon, and ſpake not one word to juſtify him; neither acquainted he him of this Conſult, for fear, it may be, he ſhould ſuſpect him, or others look on him as a Traitor to his King; thus far he is worthier of Praiſe than Cenſure. He ſhould have deteſted the Crime, but not condemn'd the Criminal; he ſhould have executed <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Orders, but not inflam'd his Choler and Revenge. As fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me, I am ready to think that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:62981:35"/> ambition of augmenting his Fortune from the ruins of <hi>Philotus</hi>'s, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the immenſe Riches of his Brother-in-Law, a Grandeur o'retopping his, induc'd him to preſs his Execution. Thus does Intereſt triumph in baſe Spirits over Duty and Friendſhip; thus is private hatred co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with the Vail of Juſtice; thus are the Sacred Laws of Equity made Inſtruments of Wrath and Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>Certainly <hi>Alexander</hi> merits eternal Praiſe for with-holding <hi>Caenus</hi> his Hand. Though he ardently deſir'd <hi>Philotas</hi> his Death, he defers it till the Army, that might have declar'd him innocent, has had perfect intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of his Crime. He rather chuſes to reſcue <hi>Philotas</hi> from being tortur'd, and to deliver him over to be judged by the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> than to oppreſs him by his own Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> having ended his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, withdrew from the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62981:35"/> A Prince ſhould never be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the condemnation of a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, nor at any thing elſe that may make him be eſteemed cruel and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible. So that leaving to the Judges the liberty of Condemning or Abſolving, he will acquire himſelf in the Hearts of the People, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of being Juſt. He will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void likewiſe ſhewing favour to the Criminal, which 'tis dangerous to refuſe, being requeſted by an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly touched with Compaſſion. Tho ſeverity in a Prince, when it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not to cruelty, as in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion more proper than Clemency, to attract the Fear and Love of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; it concerns nevertheleſs the Policy of a great Monarch ſeldom to refuſe theſe ſorts of Favours, which are a great proof of his Power and Bounty. But it concerns his Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence too, to avoid the perſecution of the Criminal's Friends or Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by a prompt execution of the Sentence paſſed by the Judges.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:62981:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philotas</hi> having liberty to ſpeak, ſaid thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>As naked Truth, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, has much more force than an Eloquent and Elaborate Diſcourſe, ſo Innocence ought not to ſeek out words for its Defence. I ſhould have held my peace, had not the King, who was foreſtall'd, incenſed you againſt me; his Speech is a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Death, which now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make him revoke, is to call him Cruel and Unjuſt. So that conſidering I muſt condemn <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s Judgment, I cannot reſolve to ask for Abſolution. His ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence declares that my deſtruction is reſolv'd upon; and what can I hope for, if the beſt of my Judges be inexorable? However <hi>Philotas</hi> ſhall not die without clearing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of the Crime he ſtands charg'd with. What Proof have they? Am I of the number of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators? Did <hi>Nicomachus</hi> name me to his Brother, or <hi>Dymnus</hi> to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comachus?</hi>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:62981:36"/> Who inquiring after the Names of thoſe that had conſpir'd the Death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the Order of the Conſpiracy; the other ingages in it through the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their Birth and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: How could <hi>Dymnus</hi> then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me, that am thought their Head? Did he fear deſtroying me? He that had ſo great a confidence in <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machus;</hi> he, I ſay, that ventur'd with him his own Life, and the Lives of his beſt Friends? <hi>Ceballi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the only Witneſs againſt me, is not of the Conſpiracy, can he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that I am? he that diſcover'd it to me? <hi>Dymnus</hi> is dead, he never nam'd me. His Confederates ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving him, may hope for Pardon, if they can caſt their Crime on me. Yet there's none accuſes me. What! cannot Tortures wreſt the Truth from them, to whom, as 'tis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the Miſerable, the ingaging others in their Misfortunes, would be ſome comfort? Do they believe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62981:37"/> in the condition I am in, abandon'd, condemn'd, I am able to deliver them from their Tortures? So you ſee, Fellow-Souldiers, the truth of the firſt Crime I am accus'd of. I come now to the ſecond; The King ſays, I daigned not to adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe him of the imminent Peril that threatned him; I was not at all troubled at it. 'Tis true, Sir, I was to blame, but you have par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd me. You invited me to Sup with you in token of a Reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. At leaſt you ought not to condemn me without hearing my Defence. What new Crime have I committed? Whence comes my Diſgrace ſince yeſterday-evening? I expected nothing leſs than this diſmal change. The Wicked are continually troubled with the Image of their Crime. Their Souls agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a thouſand different Thoughts, keep them perpetually alarm'd, preſs'd with remorſe of Conſcience, they ſeek for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62981:37"/> The eaſe <hi>Attarras</hi> found in apprehending me, diſcovers the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle care I took of my preſervation. When he bound me with Chains, I was in a deep ſleep; I rely'd upon the credit of your word; I feared not that the malice of my Enemies ſhould prevail with your Clemency. Further, Sir, could I fear any thing as to your Life, upon the bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a Youth of no Reputation, who deſtitute of all proof, could do nothing but make a vain Alarm. I ſuſpected him too, becauſe he came not to me himſelf; and look'd on it as ſome private revenge, not fit for me to meddle with. I feared likewiſe, that he might deny what he had told <hi>Ceballinus,</hi> and that I might have nothing but regret, for ſo lightly committing the chief Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Court. But for all theſe Precautions, I am ſacrific'd to thoſe I have ſpar'd. 'Tis objected, <hi>Dymnus</hi> anticipated his Puniſhment by a voluntary Death. Knew I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62981:38"/> that he would kill himſelf? If <hi>Cebal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> his Relation have no other ground but this, what does it prove againſt me? Again, had I bin a Confederate, how could I have bin ſo quiet two days after the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy was detected? I could eaſily have diſpatch'd <hi>Ceballinus,</hi> or haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en'd the ſtroke. I was alone with the King in his Chamber; who could have hinder'd me? Did I want <hi>Dymnus</hi> his preſence? 'Twas he then that was the Head of the Conſpiracy, and yet 'tis I, as is ſaid, that would have made my ſelf King of <hi>Macedonia.</hi> Whom among you, Fellow-Souldiers, have I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to corrupt? On whom have I beſtowed Preſents? What Officers are there more than ordinary ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of my Favours? I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for deſpiſing the Language of <hi>Macedonians:</hi> What likelihood is there of it, if I intend to make my ſelf their King. You know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, that ſince we have left our
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62981:38"/> own Country, and have learnt ſtrange Tongues, 'tis to all of us ſome trouble to ſpeak our own. <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf uſes it not; therefore he deſpiſes the <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> In truth, all theſe Reproaches are but light, as well as that of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Friend to <hi>Amyntas,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt <hi>Alexander.</hi> If it be a Crime to be a Friend to a King's Brother, I am guilty; but if his Birth ingag'd me in thoſe Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for him, can I not be inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, becauſe I did not divine? What juſtice is there, that the Frieds of the Guilty ſhould be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with them? I ought to have died long ſince had this Friendſhip bin a Crime: and if it be not, Why is it brought in for my deſtruction? But I pitied the condition of thoſe that were to live under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of a Man that equall'd himſelf to the Gods. 'Tis true, I wrote thus to <hi>Alexander;</hi> but told I it any elſe? Gave he me not the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62981:39"/> liberty to diſcover my Sentiments to him? Had I not reaſon to fear that his Vanity might render him odious to his People? If he have ſuch Faith in the Oracle, let him conſult it touching my Crime: <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> will never conceal a Secret of ſuch conſequence to his Son's Life. And if you'l rather truſt to Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I am ready to undergo them. My misfortunes diſpence with my introducing my Relations. I had two Brothers, they both died in Battel for <hi>Alexander</hi>'s and Your Glory. I have only a Father left, accus'd of the ſame Crime with me; neither the Grandeur of his Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the conſideration of his Age, nor his paſſion for the King, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing againſt the cruelty of thoſe that envy him. Miſerable Wretch! muſt I then, dear Father, be the cauſe of your Death? Did you give me Life to deprive you of yours? Is this the Recompence of ſo many Battels gain'd? of ſo much
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62981:39"/> Blood ſpilt in your Family? Is this the Comfort you expected from me in your laſt days? Nature was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to redemand your Life full of Glory; in the next Battel, the Grandeur of your Courage would have laid you bleeding in the midſt of your Trophies; but your Enemies not contented to deprive you of an only Son, envy you the glory of a Death that would have render'd you immortal. But, tell me, was <hi>Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi> himſelf believ'd, when he wrote to <hi>Alexander,</hi> how that <hi>Philip</hi> his Phyſician, corrupted by <hi>Darius</hi> his Gifts and Promiſes, had ingag'd to poiſon him? The King gave ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle credit to his Letter, that he gave it <hi>Philip</hi> to read whilſt he took his Phyſick, to mock, as it were, at my Father's credulity. I have made my ſelf too the Subject of Rallery, for having too lightly believed things more probable than what <hi>Ceballinus</hi> inform'd me. If I give Information, I make my ſelf ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:62981:40"/> if I hold my Peace, I am look'd on as a Criminal; what ſhould I do them?</q>
               </p>
               <p>Preſently one of the Company cry'd out; <hi>Not conſpire againſt the Life of your Prince and Benefactor.</hi> 
                  <q>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou art, thou haſt ſpoken wiſely, (anſwered <hi>Philotas</hi>) and if I am guilty of that Crime, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn my ſelf to the worſt of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments. And here I make an end, ſince you ſeem unmov'd at the conſideration of my Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and my laſt words have kindled your Choler.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philotas</hi> his laſt words ſeemed nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to proceed from a Man that was innocent, nor from one that had that courage he ſhould have in the worſt of Fortunes. A good Conſcience never deſpairs in bad Fortune; had but <hi>Philotas,</hi> guilty as he was, had the confidence to anſwer with more vigor, his Innocence would not have bin doubted, the Souldiers would have bin incited to compaſſion. A
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:62981:40"/> bold and reſolute word, utter'd in the midſt of the horrors of Death, has preſerv'd many a Criminal's Life. Nothing ſo eaſily perſwades a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, as the conſtancy of a great courage. Without doubt <hi>Philotas</hi> his Tears and Fainting were Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his Crime, as they were tokens of his Deſpair or Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>His Guards had no ſooner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey'd him from the Aſſembly, but <hi>Belon,</hi> a ſtern Man, and of a baſe Extract, who had rais'd himſelf to ſeveral Charges by his Valour, ſpake to the Souldiers with greater animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity againſt <hi>Philotas,</hi> than had bin obſerved in <hi>Alexander,</hi> in manner following.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Is it poſſible that <hi>Macedonians,</hi> who have always abhor'd Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſhould be touch'd with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion for a Traitor to his King and Country? What has he done to deſerve your Clemency? Have you not had ſufficient proof of his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:62981:41"/> Pride, of his Cruelty, of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence of his Domeſticks? How often, when we have bin tired, has he interrupted our repoſe, by the noiſe of a number of Slaves fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing at his Heels? He that drove the <hi>Macedonians</hi> from his Tent, becauſe he would have no noiſe? Which of you could ever ſpeak to him without an Interpreter, as if he only were born in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and all of us <hi>Barbarians?</hi> Did he ever make you ſenſible of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours? He that after Battel always loaded his Wagons with the Fruit of our Labours, and our Conqueſts? May we not be aſham'd that we have hitherto continu'd his Slaves, who has ſo long abuſed the King's Favour, and our Patience? He would have <hi>Hammon</hi> tell the truth, and yet he reckoned him an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor for owning <hi>Alexander</hi> for his Son. Did this Traitor conſult <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> when he conſpired againſt the Life of his King? He would only
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62981:41"/> gain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to give his Father Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, that he may come down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us with all the Forces he can raiſe in <hi>Media.</hi> Let us ſend to the Oracle, not to ſearch a Truth we are already ſufficiently inform'd of, but to return thanks for <hi>Alexander</hi>'s being preſerv'd from the Snares of this Traitor.</q>
               </p>
               <p>There needed not all this to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe the Aſſembly; there was none appeared concern'd for <hi>Philotas</hi> his miſery; they all unanimouſly breath'd Revenge; the King's Guard cried out, <hi>They ſhould let them tear the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide in pieces.</hi> But his Enemies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd him for more cruel Tortures. The King having refer'd his Sentence till the next day, called a Council, to adviſe whether it were better to have him firſt tortur'd, or immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately delivered over to be Ston'd. This laſt Opinion was moſt humane, and had bin followed, but that the cruelty of <hi>Hephaeſtion, Craterus,</hi> and <hi>Caenus</hi> was more prevalent. They
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62981:42"/> were for having him tortured, and charg'd themſelves with the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All the Inſtruments of Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were ſet before <hi>Philotas</hi> his Eyes; at which the miſerable Wreth ſhaking for fear, cried out, <q>That Rack was needleſs, ſince he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd his Crime; that he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd againſt the Life of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> that he would have taken it from him if he could; that they ſhould therefore ſpeedily give him the Death he deſerved.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Craterus,</hi> glad of an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to exerciſe his private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, perſiſted in it, that they muſt extort from him who were his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. In vain did he implore the Gods of his Country, and the King's Mercy. He was put to the Rack; his Judges were his Enemies and Tormentors; Scourges and Fire could hardly ſatisfy their fury. A ſtrange thing! <hi>Philotas</hi> but a little before deſpairing at the ſight of his Puniſhment, was, as it were, inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:62981:42"/> in the midſt of Torment. The pain he endur'd, could not wreſt one word from him; and he ſuffered all that cruelty and vengeance could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, till ſuch time, as mangled all over, he promiſed to diſcover what he knew. His Tormentors were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to retire; Then addreſſing himſelf to <hi>Craterus, Tell me,</hi> ſays he, <hi>what thou wouldst have me ſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There's no greater trouble, than that of being expoſed to the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of Enemies; the Soul feels greater pain, than the Body groaning under the cruelty of Tortures. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotas,</hi> who indured the Rack with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving one groan, could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain his Choler. <hi>Craterus</hi> not well brooking this deriſion, calls again for his Tormentors. Then <hi>Philotas,</hi> vanquiſh'd by the rigor of his Stripes, and infeebled by the great quantity of Blood he had loſt, demanded re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpit, and began afterwards to tell them, <q>how that <hi>Hegelochus,</hi> a Man of courage, and ambitious, who
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62981:43"/> died at the laſt Battel, not induring to worſhip <hi>Alexander</hi> as the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> reſolved to take away his Life; and not being able, continu'd he, to accompliſh ſo great a Deſign himſelf, he endeavour'd to engage my Father and me it. What, ſaid <hi>Hegelochus,</hi> ſhall we live under the tyranny of a Monſter? Who, though he is the wicked'ſt of Men, is not aſham'd to trace his Original from the Gods? If he have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to abuſe <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf, then what can we expect from his Vanity? His Pride was inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to us before the Oracle's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwer; and ſince, 'tis grown to that height of inſolence, that not content with our Blood and Lives, he requires from us a baſe complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, nothing l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs than adoration. <hi>Parmenio,</hi> purſu'd <hi>Philota,</hi> was very much aſtoniſhed at this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; the next day he talk'd with me about it, and not knowing whether <hi>Hegelochus</hi> had bin tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62981:43"/> with Choler, or warmed with Wine, he ſent a Meſſenger to deſire him to come to him. Being come, he ſaid the ſame he had done the Evening before, and as it ſeem'd, with more reſolution, adding, That if we would be the chief of the Conſpiracy, he would undertake to execute it. <hi>Parmenio</hi> and I having given him our Faith, thought it beſt to wait till the death of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> that all the Orient might be the reward of that Enterprize. As for that of <hi>Dymnus,</hi> I ſwear by the Life of <hi>Alexander,</hi> I never knew any thing of it: And why ſhould I diſown an Attempt, that would be no greater Crime than the other.</q>
               </p>
               <p>His Judges thought he had not ſaid enough yet. They had him tortur'd a-freſh; and <hi>Craterus,</hi> who had not fully ſatisfied his revenge, was glad of having further time to exerciſe his fury againſt him. In fine, <hi>Philotas</hi> finding himſelf no longer
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:62981:44"/> able to undergo the violence of his Tortures, confeſs'd, <q>That he was the Head of that laſt Conſpiracy, that his Fathers Age and Authority had equally induc'd him to it; that ſeeing him Head of a powerful Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Maſter of <hi>Media,</hi> and the King's Treaſury; and fearing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that if he did not make haſte, <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s Death might deprive him of the opportunity of making himſelf King, he had conceived this execrable Deſign: As for the reſt, that <hi>Parmenio</hi> was no ways guilty; that he never had communicated his Intention to him; for proof of which, they might, if they would, put him again to the Rack.</q>
               </p>
               <p>His Judges fearing he might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in his Tortures, were oblig'd to let them ceaſe, to reſerve him for a death more ignominious, as it was publick. They returned therefore to the King, and acquainted him with the Criminal's Confeſſion. <hi>Alexander</hi> commanded them to bring him the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:62981:44"/> next day to the Aſſembly, deſiring that he might own what he had ſaid in the preſence of the <hi>Macedonians. Philotas</hi> his Depoſition was then publickly read, and acknowledged by him; and <hi>Demetrius,</hi> one of his principal Confederates, was introduc'd. Never did the moſt Innocent Man appear more concern'd for a Reproach caſt upon him, than <hi>Demetrius,</hi> guilty as he was, ſeem'd offended at the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination made into his Crime: which he diſown'd with all the confidence of a good Conſcience, and proffer'd himſelf to be rack'd to ſhew his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence. His impudence ſtir'd up <hi>Philotas</hi> his Choler, who looking round about him, ſpied a young Man called <hi>Calis,</hi> and asked him, <hi>How he could ſuffer</hi> Demetrius <hi>to ſtand ſo impudently in a Lye? Calis,</hi> whoſe imprudence brought him thither, knew not what to anſwer: and the <hi>Macedonians</hi> believed that <hi>Philotas</hi> accus'd as well the Innocent as Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But as ſoon as the Youth ſaw
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:62981:45"/> himſelf incompaſs'd with Guards, he confeſs'd his Crime, and charg'd <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calis</hi> his Confeſſion, ſhews how falſe it is what ſome Authors have written touching <hi>Philotas</hi> his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; For how could he know that this young Man was of the Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy, if he were not in it himſelf, ſince neither <hi>Ceballinus,</hi> nor <hi>Nicoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> nam'd him?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pholotas</hi> and all his Confederates, according to the cuſtom of <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> were immediately ſlain with Stones, whilſt this miſerable Wretch had the power to diſown ſo deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Crime. The Souldiers were touch'd with his Misfortune. A lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more conſtancy would have ſav'd him from Death. 'Tis moſt certain <hi>Alexander</hi> ran the risk of loſing his Life, and of ſeeing all his Souldiers revolt. They were inclined to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; they pitied the deplorable Condition of <hi>Parmenio,</hi> whom they loved as their Father; and his Son
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:62981:45"/> had never bin ſacrificed to the fury of his Enemies, had he but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued firm. But when they ſaw that he confeſs'd Conſpiracy upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, Crime upon Crime, their Pity was converted into Rage, and they all maſſacred him as a Parri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Macedonians</hi> had a cruel cuſtom; When any of them was convicted for conſpiring the Death of their King, that attempt was not only puniſh'd in the Perſon of the Criminal, but his Relations receiv'd the ſame Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Almoſt all the Perſons of Quality, and brave Souldiers in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi>'s Army, were either <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> his Relations, Friends, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates. For fear of meeting with the ſame Entertainment, ſome of them provided for their ſecurity by flight; and others deſpairing of theirs, kill'd themſelves. Without doubt the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of ſo many brave Men would have rais'd a tumult in the Camp, had not <hi>Alexander</hi> proclaim'd a Pardon
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:62981:46"/> to all the Conſpirators Relations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntas</hi> and <hi>Simmias</hi> were excepted. The flight of <hi>Polemon,</hi> their younger Brother, was the pretext of their diſgrace; the true cauſe, the ſtrict friendſhip they had always had with <hi>Philotas.</hi> The King on his account beſtowed ſeveral Favors on them; and the care this unfortunate Man took to raiſe his Friends, brought them into the ſame miſery with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>Alexander</hi> perſwading himſelf that they were of the Conſpiracy, endeavour'd to have them condemn'd as well as the reſt. He repreſented therefore to his Souldiers, <q>That he had reaſon long ſince to ſuſpect the fidelity of <hi>Amyntas</hi> and his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that his Mother <hi>Olympias</hi> had given him notice of their evil In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; that the private Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between them and <hi>Philotas</hi> increaſed his ſuſpicion; that the flight of their Brother was the effect of a bad Conſcience; that they had bin all three not long ſince with
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:62981:46"/> him, had diſmiſs'd the reſt of their Company, and would have execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their Deſign, but that the Guards coming in prevented them; that the day before <hi>Philotas</hi> was taken; <hi>Antiphanes,</hi> Commiſſary of the Horſe, having demanded Horſes from <hi>Amyntas</hi> for thoſe that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, he had inſolently refus'd them, and threatned him beſides; that this arrogancy could proceed from nothing elſe but their conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Death, and the hopes they had of accompliſhing their Deſign on the Morrow. That in fine, after ſo many proofs of their perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, there was no place left for Doubts.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntas</hi> was brought forth into the preſence of the Army, and having obtained liberty to defend himſelf, he deſired that his Chains might be taken off, and a Javelin given him; which was done accordingly as a ſure preſage of favour; for theſe badges of Honour give encouragement to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:62981:47"/> ſpeak, whereas a Criminal groaning under the weight of his Chains, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly makes but a languiſhing ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue, of little efficacy to ſtir up the compaſſion of his Judges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntas,</hi> full of hopes, repreſented, <q>That the friendſhip he had with <hi>Philotas,</hi> could not with juſtice be imputed to him as a Crime; that after that manner the chiefeſt of the Court would be found guilty; that from that height of Fortune the favour of <hi>Alexander</hi> had ſeated him in, he had attracted the reſpect or envy of every one; that none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to purchaſe the King's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, if he were not ſupported by the friendſhip and protection of <hi>Philotas,</hi> 'twas no ſtrange thing that every one ſhould court him; that they had with <hi>Alexander</hi> eſteem'd his Zeal, his Courage, the Grandeur of his Services, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Merit, but that they deteſted his Crime; that they had had pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Conferences with him, but that
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:62981:47"/> this had bin all along their cuſtom. In fine, That they had hated <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> when they knew him a Parricide and diſloyal, as much as they had loved him whilſt a happy Favorite, and Arbiter of the Fortune of the <hi>Macedonians. He added,</hi> That if he were guilty for refuſing Horſes to <hi>Antiphanes,</hi> the other was no leſs for demanding them; that he had but two, which <hi>Antiphanes</hi> would have taken away by force, though he could not ſpare them without being reduced to the neceſſity of fighting on foot among the Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. For the reſt, that the ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Olympias</hi> were to be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for that being ſent into <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> he had, by <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, drawn out Troops thence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Queen's pleaſure; that from his Obedience and Services, ſprang the reſentment of <hi>Olympias,</hi> that they ſhould therefore puniſh him for having faithfully ſerved his King, and obeyed his Orders.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:62981:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amyntas</hi> was interrupted by the noiſe of thoſe that brought back his Brother <hi>Polemon</hi> bound in Chains. The Multitude ſeeing him in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Criminal, could hardly forbear ſtoning him. But the young Man, for deſpair of having thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his Brothers, proffer'd to die, on condition their Lives might be preſerv'd. As he was extream beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, and had committed no other Fault but flying, all the Souldiers were ſo mov'd at his Repentance, that they unanimouſly cried out, <hi>Theſe brave Men deſerved their Pardon. Alexander</hi> was prevail'd with, but <hi>Amyntas</hi> was inexorable; the King commanded him at laſt to forgive <hi>Polemon,</hi> as he had done, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd the Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polydamus</hi> was <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s chiefeſt Friend; in Battel he had him always at his ſide, to make him, as it were, participant of his Glory; he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich'd him with his Favours, and had more confidence in him than any.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:62981:48"/> 
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> cauſing him to be called, commanded him to bring in his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom he kept as Hoſtages, and ſpake to him in manner follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s attempt has wrong'd you more than any, for under ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of Juſtice and Zeal for my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he has particularly oblig'd you to his Intereſts. All his Favours, all his Friendſhip tended to no other end than to corrupt you, and to render you a Complice to his Treachery. 'Tis you therefore that muſt revenge his Infidelity, and the Ingratitude he has ſhewn towards me. See what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence I have in you, that I have choſen you to carry theſe Letters to my Lieutenants in <hi>Media.</hi> You ſhall preſent two to <hi>Parmenio,</hi> one from me, and one from his Son, for I have his Seal; he will not doubt of any thing when he ſees you. In the mean time I will keep your Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as Pledges to aſſure me of your Faith; and when you have
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:62981:49"/> executed my Orders, your fidelity ſhall be rewarded.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polydamas</hi> was ſo allarm'd when the King cauſed him to be called, and commanded him to bring in his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that he utterly deſpaired of Life, becauſe of the intimate friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between him and <hi>Parmenio.</hi> Thinking therefore on nothing more than the danger he had eſcaped, and forgetting what he owed his Friend, he promiſed <hi>Alexander</hi> more than he required. Here you may obſerve the Frailty of Court-friendſhip. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt gives it its Original, and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune changes it every moment: If you are happy, you are ador'd; if you are miſerable, you are inſulted over.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polydamus</hi> imploys all diligence, arrives in <hi>Media</hi> by Night, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly delivers the King's Letters to his Lieutenants. Upon which they immediately aſſemble in <hi>Cleander</hi>'s A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, and deliberate on means to take away <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s Life. They
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:62981:49"/> reſolved therefore to go to him the next day all in Company, to execute <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Orders.</p>
               <p>Unfortunate <hi>Parmenio</hi> was walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them in a Park, when <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus,</hi> whom he had ſent for, was brought unto him. He runs preſently to imbrace him, and being glad to hear from his King, and to ſee his Friend, he receives him with extream joy. <hi>Polydamas</hi> having given him <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Letter, <hi>Parmenio</hi> after he had read it, told them, <q>That he could not but admire that the King, after ſo many Conqueſts, ſhould yet think of ſubduing the <hi>Arachoſians;</hi> That it was now time for him to return into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> there in quiet to enjoy his Victories, and the Glory he had acquir'd. After which,</q> as he was reading <hi>Philotas</hi> his Letter with great pleaſure, <hi>Cleander</hi> thruſt him into the Boſom with his Poniard and gave him another ſtab in the Throat.</p>
               <p>Thus expir'd <hi>Parmenio</hi> and <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:62981:50"/> both of great credit in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, both intimate Friends of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> the moſt puiſſant of all the Nobility of the Empire; the braveſt of Captains; the moſt illuſtrious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Macedonians.</hi> The death of <hi>Philotas</hi> was miſerable, full of pain and infamy; that of <hi>Parmenio</hi> more cruel, unjuſt, and ominous to <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Life, who afterwards could find no Captain of that valour and experience in his whole Empire, nor found he afterwards the ſame zeal and affection from his Souldiers, and the chief of his Nobility.</p>
               <p>We all die alike, but Death is not equally grievous to us all. If it be the end of our Miſeries, we deſire it, we ſeek it, we run to it; but if it terminate a Life full of Happineſs, Grandeur, Glory, and Delights, it fills us with deſpair. <hi>Parmenio</hi> had liv'd ſeventy Years in all proſperity, he had expos'd himſelf to ſeveral Dangers in his King's Service; he had bin the Companion of his Victories,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:62981:50"/> and had done many glorious Actions worthy the envy of Kings; illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous both in Peace and War: he died aſſaſſin'd by his Confidents, upon Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions not well clear'd, and by <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s Order, who was indebted to him for his Empire.</p>
               <p>There's nothing more fit to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Courts of Princes to than the Sea. There's no greater pleaſure than to fail on this Element during a Calm. Some Voyages by Sea are as pleaſant as profitable; but 'tis dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to make them a Profeſſion, ſince early or late one muſt periſh in them. You'l ſay there's this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, That it is not in the power of Man to lay a Storm, but that the Sage can in Princes Courts moderate his Paſſions, and not ſuffer himſelf to be carried away with too much Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Teach us this Leſſon your ſelf, and ſhew us how to curb Envy.</p>
               <p>Some ſmall reflection upon <hi>Philotas</hi> his Conſpiracy, will eaſily inform us how much more difficult it is for a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:62981:51"/> Courtier, elevated to the higheſt pitch of Favour, to moderate his Ambition, than for another who has every thing yet to wiſh for. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs the latter has but one ſtep to the accompliſhment of Grandeur, and the former is infinitely diſtant from it. The higheſt fortune of a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter differs as far from Royalty, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power from the obedience of Subjects. 'Tis therefore a folly to think the aſcent to a Throne eaſy for being near it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:62981:51"/>
               <head>THE CONSPIRACY OF <hi>HERMOLAUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe conſideration of a Danger happily avoided, renders the Sage more moderate and cautious; whereas all the effect it has on a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage Spirit, is to make it more extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, raſh, and arrogant. The fear <hi>Alexander</hi> had of the laſt Conſpiracy, was like that of thoſe who ſee the falling of a Thunder-Bolt without receiving any dammage. They fear juſt at that moment, and preſently forget the Danger; like thoſe that come to themſelves from Swooning, incapable to make reflection on an evil they have not felt. Add to this
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:62981:52"/> that Confidence more dangerous than the Peril it ſelf, and ſo common to Man, whereby he fears not a Danger paſt, though when imminent it nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly concern'd his Life. Some yet more irrational, are ſo foreſtalled with their good Fortune, that they imagine themſelves above Fate, and ſuch are oftentimes reſerv'd for a tragical and miſerable Cataſtrophe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> grew ſo outragious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Parmenio,</hi> that he knew no Limits; the risk he ran in the laſt Conſpiracy, render'd him leſs provident, he thought he might for the future freely injure the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> The facility wherewith he had quell'd <hi>Parmenio</hi> and <hi>Philotas,</hi> made him more bold and inſolent; he thought himſelf King indeed, when he ſaw that he was Arbiter of his Subjects Lives, and that there was nothing more to be done to place himſelf beyond the reach of Envy, than to ſhed the beſt Blood in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia.</hi> The more you commend the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:62981:52"/> vanity of great Ones, the more are they in love with it; the more Blood a Tyrant ſheds, the more is he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of ſhedding it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lynceſtes Alexander</hi> had bin im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon'd three Years, upon an Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of two Witneſſes, for conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſt the Life of <hi>Alexander;</hi> the Reaſon his Puniſhment had bin ſo long defer'd was, becauſe he was the firſt that ſaluted <hi>Alexander</hi> King after the death of <hi>Philip. Antipater, Lynceſtes</hi> his Father-in-Law, was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Macedonia;</hi> and it ſeem'd very probable, that the interceſſion of one that was Maſter of ſo flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing a Kingdom, ſhould have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpended his execution a far longer time. But <hi>Alexander</hi> would no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger hearken to Policy: an inſatiable deſire of revenge carried him on to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his own ruin. He cauſed therefore the Criminal to be brought forth, accuſed only by two Perſons, and had him diſpatch'd according to their cuſtom.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:62981:53"/>
               <p>The Chief of the <hi>Macedonians</hi> perceived preſently that <hi>Alexander</hi> grew more cruel from day to day, and began to fear for themſelves. They were ready to think, that the Heavens provok'd by the King's va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, who dared equal himſelf to the Gods, had inſpir'd <hi>Philotas</hi> with the deſire of taking away his Life. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſpread this Rumor through the Army, the eaſier to engage the Souldiers to a revolt.</p>
               <p>The remembrance of <hi>Parmenio</hi>'s Merit, and <hi>Philotas</hi> his Misfortune, who died in the flower of his Age, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready excited pity in the <hi>Macedonians.</hi> In the one they thought they had loſt the Protector of their Liberty, the Avenger of the Gods and of their Country; in the other a Captain of rare Valour, without whom <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> could do nothing that was great. Theſe ſeditious Diſcourſes would have forg'd a Rebellion, had not the King cauſed his Army to march againſt the <hi>Arachoſians.</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:62981:53"/> doubt that was the only means to diſſipate all ill Deſigns. Idleneſs ſpoils the Souldiers Spirits, but all theſe murmurs vaniſh at the firſt ſound of the Trumpet.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Conduct might well have made ſuch brave Men deſperate. For having known that ſeveral highly reſented <hi>Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio</hi>'s Death, he form'd them into a Body, and made <hi>Leonidas</hi> their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ordering them to incamp ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately from the reſt, as it were, out of ignominy. It was not to be feared that their ſeditious Diſcourſes ſhould have corrupted the reſt of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians;</hi> for, as is the cuſtom of Souldiers, Martial Liberty, and the joy of new Conqueſts, would have laid their Anger and their Malice.</p>
               <p>In the mean while <hi>Alexander</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon'd himſelf to all ſorts of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The irregularity of his Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners increaſed with his Victories, and his Ambition no longer curb'd by Vertue, carried him to that exceſs of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:62981:54"/> Pride, as to require from the <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> Divine Honours. I cannot but pity the weakneſs and vanity of this Prince. Could he think the <hi>Macedonians</hi> would wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as a God, one born of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Olympias,</hi> ſubject to the ſame In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities with other Men? Theſe Heroës, whom Antiquity has placed in the Heavens, lived in ſuch ſort, that Poſterity reckon'd them in the number of the Gods after their Death; and if during their Life they ſhould have required from Men Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Divine Worſhip, without doubt they would have render'd themſelves deſpicable and ridiculous to the whole World. The Sages forbore not to ſcoff at thoſe falſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinities; and the more enlightned <hi>Pagans</hi> have themſelves laugh'd at their own Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> preſum'd too much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Grandeur of his Actions: the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and other ſtrange Nations, might well admire them; but the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:62981:54"/> 
                  <hi>Macedonians</hi> could do no more than praiſe his Conduct and his Courage. Thoſe that run the ſame danger, are willing to participate with the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral in the Glory of the Conflict, and ſuffer with regret that any one ſhould attribute to himſelf the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Victory. But if he were ſo intent to elevate himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the condition of Men, why was he not more diligent to gain reſpect from his People? It is not for the Majeſty of a Prince to make himſelf too publick: if he will be ador'd, he muſt ſeparate himſelf from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the World.</p>
               <p>The old <hi>Macedonian</hi> Captains taking it ill that <hi>Alexander</hi> ſhould publickly debaſe his Father's Glory, ſcoffed at his Pride and pretended Divinity. Which ſo incenſed him, that he kill'd <hi>Clitus,</hi> his Nourſes Son, with a Javelin. This great Warrier, who had ſav'd his Life at the Battel of <hi>Granicus,</hi> ſuffered with regret his ſo outragiouſly attacking the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:62981:55"/> of <hi>Philip,</hi> and abhor'd his Vanity, and the enormity of his Crimes. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was he without a Second; <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſthenes,</hi> who made profeſſion of Wiſdom, declar'd himſelf more open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for as <hi>Cleo</hi> one day, at Table with the chief of the <hi>Macedonians</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> propounded to render Divine Honour to <hi>Alexander;</hi> This Philoſopher anſwered him with his uſual freedom, <q>That it was not in the power of Men to make a God, that they could hardly make a King; and that the <hi>Perſians</hi> would be their Conquerors, if they followed them in their barbarous Cuſtoms.</q> The freedom that <hi>Polypercon</hi> took was yet greater, who ſeeing a <hi>Perſian</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping the King, began to laugh, and throwing him upon his Face, bad him <hi>bow lower.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe Scoffs tended to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Glory: How then could he expect Divine Honour from thoſe that ſo much contemn'd him? For this he muſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:62981:55"/> have chang'd the form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; have made himſelf abſolute Monarch of the Empire; have uſurp'd the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Freedom; have bin Arbiter of their Lives and Fortunes; have diſpatch'd his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles; and have kept ſuch a diſtance between himſelf and his Subjects, as might have made him ſeem quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what he was. But if the horror of ſo great an Impiety, or the neceſſity he then had for his Captains, permitted him not to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to that exceſs of Cruelty; it concern'd his prudence and wiſdom to moderate his Ambition; and the friendſhip of his Nobility would have bin far more glorious, than the adoration of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the baſe complaiſance of that Nation.</p>
               <p>'Twas this unreaſonable Pride which made him again run the risk of loſing his Life, which at laſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated him to his ruin, and has render'd his Memory odious to all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:62981:56"/> Ages. The Death of <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> is certainly deplorable, and a great proof of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Wickedneſs, who could not ſuffer an honeſt Man in his ſight. In fine, he fell on a ſudden from that moderation that had made him admir'd and lov'd of every one, to ſo violent Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, and to ſo great profuſion of Vice, that 'tis no wonder that <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molaus</hi> ſhould have the boldneſs to conſpire his Death.</p>
               <p>The Noblemens Children of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonia,</hi> according to cuſtom, were oblig'd to enter into the King's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at fifteen Years of Age. After ſome Years the Prince promoted them to the higheſt Charges; of them came Favorites, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Captains. According to all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, theſe young Nobles were more likely than any to tolerate their Prince's Defects and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as having bin for a long time accuſtom'd to his Humour, and brought up in his Court as Sons.
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:62981:56"/> But as it is impoſſible intirely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave Lions of their natural fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; ſo there is in humane Nature ſomething ſo fierce and indomitable, that though it may for ſome time be kept under, it can never be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd; there is a ſelf-love which is, as it were, the meaſure and firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of all our Affections; there is a Liberty which the weight of Chains cannot bow.</p>
               <p>Who could have thought that theſe young Nobles, having contriv'd a Conſpiracy againſt <hi>Alexander,</hi> (ſo much the more dangerous, as they were driven by a deſire of Glory, and an implacable hatred) and given each other their Faith, ſhould neither by the careſſes of their Prince, nor the inconſtancy of their Age, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to violate the ſame for a long time; all but one obſerving it intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which is rare in Traitors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> being one day a Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Hermolaus,</hi> one of his Pages, threw his Dart at a Wild Boar and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:62981:57"/> kill'd him. The King, who was run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in to preſent the Beaſt with his Spear, conceiving indignation againſt <hi>Hermolaus,</hi> cauſed him to be whipp'd according to the cuſtom of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians.</hi> But this young Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not brooking the Affront, ſhew'd, that thoſe who are ſo far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd in Years, as to be able to take up Reſolutions beſeeming Men of courage, are not to be dealt withal as Children. Nothing is more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to incite a reſolute and ambitious Spirit to revenge, than the receiving ſhameful Puniſhment for a bold and generous Action, worthy of a Prince's Applauſe. Virtue has its Venom; 'tis dangerous to provoke it; we ſee daily Pity converted into Fury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermolaus</hi> in diſpair ſeeks out <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſthenes,</hi> that wiſe Philoſopher, and enemy to Flattery, famous for his Learning, and the auſterity of his Manners. Preſently he complains to him with tears of the out-rage he has receiv'd; and 'tis reported, that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:62981:57"/> 
                  <hi>Caliſthenes,</hi> whether it were to incite him to revenge, or to comfort him, ſaid to him; <hi>Conſider,</hi> Hermolaus, <hi>that thou art now no Child.</hi> Theſe words gave him ſuch courage, that from that very inſtant he conſpir'd the death of <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Counſel of great Men is held in a Common-Wealth as an Oracle and a Law; whence it comes that a Man eſteem'd wiſe by the Vulgar, can eaſily raiſe a Multitude, and cauſe a great diſorder in a State. The more powerful therefore a Man is in Counſel, the more moderate ſhould he be in giving it. <hi>Caliſthenes,</hi> whom every one heard with pleaſure, ought to have taken heed to his words more than any, under the reign of a Prince who puniſh'd the intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the Tongue with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Puniſhment. He had done like a Man of great Wiſdom, if he had only comforted <hi>Hermolaus</hi> in his diſgrace, and not ſet him on revenge, a young Man apparently incapable
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:62981:58"/> of ſuch kind of Enterprizes. One muſt be certain of the Event; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ones Enemy, or not attack him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermolaus</hi> inflam'd with a deſire of Revenge, and not being able to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh it himſelf, aſſembles his Companions, and ſpeaks to them in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If the Affront I received only concern'd me, I would only lament my diſgrace, and impute it to my bad Fortune. But all the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> have part in my Infamy, and it concerns their Glory to take a memorable Revenge. Doubtleſs the Gods, jealous of their own Grandeur, have ſuffer'd <hi>Alexander,</hi> who dares equal himſelf to them, to deal with us ſo unworthily, that they might inſpire us with a juſt reſentment, and courage to free our ſelves from this Monſter of Pride. Be not deceived, my Companions, I have not bin puniſh'd according to Law: <hi>Alexander</hi> could not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:62981:58"/> that I ſhould rob him of the Glory of killing a Wild Boar; he has exerciſed his private Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Envy is the only cauſe of this outrage. I have done a bold Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit for my Age, fit to be admir'd, and he has treated me like a Slave. What recompence can you now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect for your great Services, if In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude and Ignominy be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of Courage? What avails it you, <hi>Macedonians,</hi> that you have gain'd by the price of your Blood, the Empire of the Univerſe? Were it not better to be in bondage to the <hi>Perſians?</hi> A generous Action gives a Slave his Liberty, which we loſe in the midſt of Victories. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier the Vanquiſh'd than the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhers, under the Government of a Tyrant? He cannot ſuffer the Glory of the latter, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly the Object of his Fury, whereas the former come not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reach of Envy. I ſcruple not to ſay that <hi>Alexander</hi> is a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:62981:59"/> What fitter name can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to one that is ſo greedy of his own Citizens Blood? How ſhall I find words to expreſs his Impiety, his Cruelty, his Arrogance? Is he not a Monſter, to make himſelf Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter of Mens Lives, and the Glory of the Gods? who would be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of our Bodies, and Tyrant o're our Hearts? who not content to reign on Earth, would have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in Heaven? He is not aſham'd to require Honours that another would refuſe; and becauſe we free <hi>Macedonians,</hi> laugh at the baſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> he hates us, he lays Snares for us, he oppreſſes us. See how he recompences thoſe to whom he is indebted for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> his Glory and his Life. His inſolence aſcends to that degree of impiety, as to make us own for the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> a wicked perfidious Deſertor, who forſakes the Laws of his Country to follow the Cuſtoms of <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:62981:59"/> whom we have known born of <hi>Olympias;</hi> who is jealous of his Father's Glory, and aſſaſſinates his beſt Friends. What do you expect, O generous Souls, a Death as cruel as that of <hi>Parmenio</hi> and <hi>Clitus?</hi> Shall we yet ſprinkle <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Laurels with our Blood, to be at laſt like thoſe great Men ſacrific'd to his fury? Conſider that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing dearer to miſerable Mortals than their Lives; ſhall we ſuffer them freely to be taken from us? Why ſhould we not rather ſecure them by <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Death? So memorable an Action will eternize our glorious Memory to poſterity. This Tyrant's Life is in our Hands, the Heavens have given him over to our Vengeance; in us, whom he has cruelly injur'd, he repoſes all his confidence; would you have a more convincing proof of the Will and Anger of the Gods? Without doubt 'tis their pleaſure to make uſe of our tender Youth in ſo bold an
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:62981:60"/> Enterprize, to make it known to the World that they are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, we only their Inſtruments. Is there any of you ſo ill advis'd as to oppoſe the Gods? Incited by the Heavens, <hi>Alexander</hi>'s inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pride and Cruelty, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m'd, gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Glory, and full of firm Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſhall we not dare attack a Man without Guards, unarm'd, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd with Crimes, in a deep ſleep? I have choſen you, my Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from all others, to participate in a Glory that ſhall never die. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for your ſecurity, reſcue the Liberty of your Country; ſhake off a Yoke full of Infamy and Pain. Revenge the Gods, revenge your ſelves, join with me, and put an end to our Calamities.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This invective of <hi>Hermolaus</hi> made ſuch an Impreſſion upon the Spirits of thoſe young Nobles, that they preſently reſolv'd to take away <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s Life. <hi>Soſtratus,</hi> one of them, who lov'd <hi>Hermolaus</hi> intirely, could
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:62981:60"/> not behold the Marks of his Stripes but with extream grief, and exage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the King's Cruelty, his Friends Merit, the <hi>Macedonians</hi> Diſgrace, the injury done the Gods, the neceſſity of revenging that Affront; he ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd thoſe young Spirits, already diſpos'd for revenge, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed interchangeably to be faithful one to another, and became unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So powerful is Religion, that it has an abſolute dominion over the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. The Fealty Subjects uſually ſwear to their Soveraign, is for the moſt part inviolable, the People are ſeized with a Religious Horror when any one breaks his Faith. But we muſt not miſtake, there are two ſorts of Religions; the one draws its Original from Heaven, and being wholly Divine, has a ſecret force to make us do good; the other is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on humane fear and frailty: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all our inward Motions have no other Rule but this imperfect Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:62981:61"/> our obedience to the Laws and Magiſtrates, proceeds from the fear we have of Magiſtrates and of the Laws. When this Fear ceaſes in the Heart of Man, Religion ceaſes too. You ſee <hi>Hermolaus</hi> and <hi>Soſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> perſwade their Companions that the Gods approve of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and conſpire together with them, and upon that account they baniſh from their Hearts that fear which the Power of the Laws had till then maintained in them; they are no longer reſtrain'd by that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that is wholly Celeſtial; the Gods in their Opinion are offended at the Affront given them, they think to revenge them in revenging them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>Confederates with <hi>Hermolaus</hi> and <hi>Soſtratus</hi> were, <hi>Nicoſtratus, Antipater, Aſclepiodorus, Philotas, Articles, Elap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius,</hi> and <hi>Epimenes.</hi> At the very firſt they met with an Obſtacle in their way. They foreſaw, becauſe they could not be all on the Guard at
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:62981:61"/> once, that it would be difficult for them to execute their Deſign. But at laſt, by changing the order of the Guards, they brought it about that they were one Night altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in the Palace. 'Tis a wonder that in two and thirty days, (the time they imploy'd in taking their Meaſures) not one of them ſhould reveal a Secret intruſted to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
               <p>Souls truly generous, which act only out of a deſire of Glory, are moſt capable of ſilence. 'Twas only their Animoſity againſt the King, and the Honour they thought would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to them from that Action, that induc'd them to their Revenge. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and Intereſt, had no ſhare in it; for then likewiſe when Riches, or ſome alteration in Affairs are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, the fear of loſing what is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready poſſeſs'd, injoyns ſecreſy. Thoſe act with great courage, their deſires increaſe with the danger, and every moment ſeems to them an Age.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:62981:62"/> Theſe act nothing without Fear, at the point of Execution they trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the dread of Puniſhment makes them think of their own and their Prince's preſervation.</p>
               <p>The Night came, in which the Conſpirators intended, by treachery, to ſpoil <hi>Alexander</hi> of his Life; they ſtood waiting at the Door, whilſt the King was at Supper, for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out to go to Bed. On the one hand they were glad to ſee him ſit at Table longer than ordinary, imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it would be eaſier for them to diſpatch him, charg'd with Wine and Sleep. On the other, they feared that the pleaſure of the Repaſt might retain him till it were day, and that other Guards taking their places, they might be forced to defer the execution of their Deſign eight days longer, which put them into ſtrange diſquiets. In fine, <hi>Alexander</hi> retires, and the Conſpirators think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves certain of their Enterprize. Let a prudent and wiſe Man order
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:62981:62"/> things with the exacteſt diligence and greateſt caution, neither his caution nor his diligence ſhall be able to change the courſe of Fortune. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in my opinion is no vain ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary thing; 'tis an aſſembling of certain Circumſtances, which neither our Wiſdom can unite or ſeparate; and 'tis great raſhneſs to preſume to change the order of Fate.</p>
               <p>Juſt as <hi>Alexander</hi> was going to Bed, a Woman, accounted Fooliſh, who uſed to foretel things to come, came and told him, that he was threatned with ſome danger, and that he ſhould return and ſpend the reſt of the Night at Table. Whether it were that the King was troubled at this Diſcourſe, or that his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination perſwaded him to debauch, he ſaid, 'twas good to follow the Counſel of the Gods, and caus'd his Company to be called back.</p>
               <p>I know not why the Law forbids to give credit to thoſe that pretend to foretel things to come. A number
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:62981:63"/> of Events foreſeen ſeveral Ages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they happen'd, may perſwade us that this Science is not altogether vain. Yet notwithſtanding we muſt be ſubject to the Law, as it is the emanation of the Wiſdom of God, and not believe Hiſtories, which are oftentimes no other than meer hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Fictions.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as it was day, the Guards, according to cuſtom, were reliev'd; which notwithſtanding the Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, whom a vehement deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge puſh'd on to the execution of their Deſign, would continue ſtill. The King perſwaded that they were willing to give him a proof of their Obedience and Affection, praiſed their Zeal, and ſending them to take their Reſt, ordered fifty thouſand Seſterces a Man to be given them.</p>
               <p>What cannot a generous Action work upon the Spirit of Man? What cannot the Favours of a King effect with a Soul never ſo paſſionate? An inſatiable deſire of Avarice cauſes
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:62981:63"/> daily a thouſand baſe Actions, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Treacheries; how much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the force of Liberality, that excites acknowledgment from the moſt ingrate, that reclaims the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Tyrants, that appeaſes the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Gods. If Riches in the corruption of the Age we live in ſerve to cover the infamy of the wicked, will not Vertue, think you, accompanied with the Goods of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, appear with greater luſter? What wonder then if it be of greater force to attract the Hearts of Men? Without doubt Vice would not reign on Earth, if Vertue were but recompenced. Here Princes ſhould beſtow their Favours; this is the true means to ſecure themſelves the Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their Subjects. The deſire of Man having no other Object than Honour and Riches, there's no one but had rather merit them by faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Services, then acquire them trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly. Who is he that would prefer Ignominy before Glory, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:62981:64"/> before a Reward, that that is uncertain, and to come, before the enjoyment of a certain and preſent good? Two things render a Prince odious, and incline his Subjects to revolt. When he rewards the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the Upright with Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and vents his Favours on the Wicked and Vicious. The Honeſt, if they are in miſery, ſeek not to get out of it by ways of Honeſty; they eſteem them uſeleſs; they take the ſhorteſt way, and indeavour to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt themſelves in charges through diſſimulation, malice, and baſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance; when flattery and ſuch other indirect means fail them, their Spirits corrupted by new Maxims, and imagining that the Wicked can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without a Recompence, prompt them to Violence, Injuſtice, Treachery, and oftentimes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire their Prince's Death. Princes therefore ſhould ſeek their ſecurity in the Hearts of thoſe that live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Dominion. They ſhould
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:62981:64"/> extend their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>eroſity to all their Subjects. Not that a Monarch is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to beſtow his Favours equally on all ſorts of Perſons. Such a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence would rather attract Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, than Love and Gratitude. Preſents, like Meats, diſguſt, if they are not ſeaſon'd with juſtice and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Merit. That Prince can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eſteemed liberal, that gives indifferently to every one. That's a prodigality, proceeding neither from eſteem nor friendſhip, the only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients to gain Hearts in beſtowing Benefits. We have no acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment barely upon the account of a Benefit, our Gratitude has a more noble and worthy Object, it conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders principally the good Will and Affection of the Giver. But on the other hand, a Prince ſhould avoid being ſo inconſiderately profuſe, as to give ſo largely to his Favorites, Miniſters, or Friends, as to deprive himſelf of the means to ſhew them further Favours; nor indeed ſhould
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:62981:65"/> he remove them from the neceſſity of deſiring them; for then they grow inſolent in their good Fortune, they look on their Prince as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted Source, they contemn his Affection grown barren, they fly their Benefactor, they hate him. When a Man is elevated to the higheſt degree of his Ambition, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, and Avarice, are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable Companions of his Pride. A Prince ſhould therefore comfort the Miſerable, but not make them happy; do good, but not all the good he can; promote ſome many degrees above others, but never to the higheſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epimenes,</hi> one of the Conſpirators, whether vanquiſh'd by <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Liberality, as conſidering that he might expect both a Pardon for his Crime, and an extraordinary Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence beſides if he ſav'd his King's Life; who for a ſervice of little con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, had given him fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Seſterces; or whether fearing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:62981:65"/> the Anger of the Gods, reveal'd the Conſpiracy to his Brother <hi>Eurylochus.</hi> Who preſently carries him to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and asks to ſpeak with the King. <hi>Ptolomaeus</hi> and <hi>Leonatus,</hi> who guarded his Chamber-dore, having learnt from him, that he had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to tell the King that concern'd his Life, warn'd by <hi>Philotas</hi> his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, gave them entrance; though the King after his debauch had need of reſt. Preſently <hi>Epimenes</hi> relates the whole Order of the Conſpiracy; and <hi>Alexander,</hi> though frighten'd at the danger he had run, was glad of finding this Pretext to ruin <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſthenes.</hi> Touching whom he ask'd <hi>Eurylochus</hi> ſeveral times, if he were not a Confederate or Friend to the Conſpirators? But <hi>Eurylochus</hi> could give him no other Anſwer, than that <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> gave ear to the Invectives of thoſe that ſpake boldly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Conduct and Behaviour. <hi>Alexander</hi> nevertheleſs treated him as a Confederate; and calling to mind
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:62981:66"/> the freedom of that Philoſopher, who had refuſed to render him Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honour, he ordered him to be ſhut up cloſe Priſoner with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſevere to the Conſpirators, ſo he was liberal and grateful to <hi>Eurylochus</hi> and <hi>Epimenes.</hi> To the latter he gave his Life, to the former fifty Talents, and the confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>Tiridates</hi> his Goods, who was very rich.</p>
               <p>So great Intereſt has a Prince in recompenſing the fidelity of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that his Favours proceed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from his Juſtice than his Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. As many Favours as he confers, ſo many Sentinels has he to watch for him. Rewards have greater force than Puniſhments; and the expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Good, than the fear of Evil. The cuſtom of pardoning thoſe, that reveal Crimes themſelves are guilty of, is no leſs ancient than neceſſary. Impunity rouſes the Conſcience, cauſes it to reveal the Treaſon, and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:62981:66"/> preſerves the Life of the Prince. However ſuch Traitors are not to be confided in: and 'tis dangerous to ſeem to miſtruſt them; they are like thoſe Animals that are tam'd only for a time, early or late, they return to their firſt fierceneſs.</p>
               <p>The next day <hi>Alexander</hi> cauſed the Conſpirators, all but <hi>Caliſthenes,</hi> to be brought forth into the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. The Criminals Relations were called, and in their preſence the King ask'd thoſe Traitors, <hi>What he had done to them to induce them to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire his Death?</hi> They as reſolute, as if they had bin upon the point of executing their Deſign, anſwered him boldly, <hi>That they were ſorry they could not yet take away his Life.</hi> Theſe words ſtirr'd up the Souldiers indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; and they demanded thoſe Parricides to be deliver'd to them.</p>
               <p>A Crime, if acknowledged with ſome Tokens of Repentance, excites compaſſion; if with impudent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, it creates Horror. The
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:62981:67"/> Offence it ſelf deſerves pardon, the vanity of boaſting in it is inſufferable. For in this there is malice; the other is a weakneſs that may be born with.</p>
               <p>The King admiring the boldneſs and contumacy of theſe Youths, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to them, <hi>That he had loved them all as his Children, that not long ſince they had bin ſenſible of the effects of his Affection; that they ſhould therefore freely declare the occaſion that led them to conceive ſo deteſtable a Deſign.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At theſe words they began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; only <hi>Hermolaus,</hi> with more conſtancy than a good Conſcience could furniſh, took the word, and addreſſing himſelf to <hi>Alexander, Know you not,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that we are born free? how comes it then that you handle us like Slaves? A Tyrant, as you are, does not deſerve to live.</hi> To whom <hi>Alexander</hi> ſaid, <hi>Continue bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what thou haſt learnt of thy Maſter</hi> Caliſthenes.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I accept of thy favour, anſwer'd <hi>Hermolaus;</hi> and in giving me leave
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:62981:67"/> to ſpeak, thou ſufficiently declareſt thy impiety. Setting aſide all thy other Actions, Can there be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proof of thy licentiouſneſs, than the opinion thou haſt of the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of thy Merit? after having render'd thy ſelf unworthy of protection from the Gods, or the eſteem of Men, thou askeſt, <hi>What induc'd us to conſpire thy Death?</hi> Does there any thing repreſent it ſelf to my Eyes, or Memory, that does not mind me of thy intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Vanity, of thy Cruelty, worthy not of one, but a thouſand deaths? If I look on thee, I ſee a Monſter of Pride, who diſowns great <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> for his Father, and has the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to call himſelf the Son of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter.</hi> Nay, ſuch is thy impudence, that thou requireſt Worſhip from us, as if thou wer't really in the number of the Gods, and not the Object of their Fury. If I look upon the Army, I find I am firſt to make reflection on my ſelf; thou
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62981:68"/> haſt uſed me unworthily for coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly killing of a Wild Boar. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this I muſt pity the misfortune of ſo many brave Men, and valiant Captains; thou haſt through a cruel Ingratitude inflicted Death on thoſe that have preſerv'd thy Life. Was there ever ſuch a Tyranny heard of? Was ever the Virtue, Valour, and Love of Subjects thus rewarded? If I conſider the many Provinces we have conquer'd, this great Empire of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a better Prince, I muſt own that we our ſelves are vanquiſh'd; Strangers are our Maſters, thou thy ſelf yieldeſt to their Laws; their Cuſtoms, their Habits, their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, their Alliances, their Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Religion, which thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferreſt before our Laws, ſufficiently diſcover that they are Victors, and thou their Slave. O wretched, O deplorable condition of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians!</hi> Doſt thou ſee now what is the Subject of our Animoſity?
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:62981:68"/> The only Obligation we have from thee is, That thou wilt this day free us from a Servitude a thouſand times more ignominious and cruel than Death to generous Spirits. Happy thoſe whom thou haſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed barbarouſly to be maſſacred, <hi>Attalus, Lynceſtes, Clitus, Parmenio,</hi> and <hi>Philotas.</hi> Had they liv'd, they would yet have groan'd under thy Tyranny; the God's were pleaſed to withdraw them from a diſmal train of miſeries that thou inflicteſt on thy beſt Friends. It may be thy Affection is ſeated in the Souldiers, and the common People. O Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens! thirty thouſand Mules loaden with Gold, and the riches, ſpoils of the Enemy, follow in the rear of thy Army, when thy wretched Souldiers, of all their Conqueſts, retain nothing but Scars, illuſtrious Marks of their Courage and thy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. In fine, thou art no longer King of <hi>Macedonia;</hi> thou art a Slave to the <hi>Perſians.</hi> Their
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:62981:69"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:62981:69"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:62981:70"/> delicacy pleaſes thee more than the <hi>Macedonian</hi> temperance. We juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore purſue thee as a Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; and at moſt, it was not the King of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> but the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> that we would have kill'd. And you, <hi>Macedonians,</hi> baſe Souls, unworthy the Glory of your Anceſtors, miſerable Slaves to a Tyrant's Pride, Have you not the Hearts to ſhake off ſo infamous a Yoke? And you, my Father, that hold your Sword at my Breſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not to have given Life to ſuch a Son. This day will you acquire by my death a glorious and eternal reputation; ſuffer me then to ſpeak, and oppoſe not the liberty granted me from your God. 'Tis becauſe he fears not the words of a Child. Why heareſt thou not, <hi>Caliſthenes?</hi> To arrive to the higheſt pitch of Tyranny, I ſee thou intendeſt to ſuppreſs in him all the freedom of the <hi>Greeks.</hi> Think not that he is of the Conſpiracy, he never knew
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:62981:70"/> any thing of it; and for proof of this we all proffer our ſelves to be rack'd. Seek ſome other Pretext to ſatisfy thy revenge, cut off the only true <hi>Macedonian,</hi> in whom reſides all the virtue of our Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. For thou hateſt the looks of an honeſt Man. For the reſt, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the miſerable old Age of our Fathers, and confound not the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent with the Guilty. As for us, we die with regret, only for leaving thee alive.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Invectives ſo incens'd the Aſſembly, that the Souldiers would a hundred times have torn <hi>Hermolaus</hi> in pieces. His own Father, called <hi>Sopolis,</hi> ſometimes ſtopp'd his Mouth, ſometimes preſented his Sword to his Breſt to make him hold his peace; but <hi>Alexander</hi> commanded him to retire. <hi>Sopolis</hi> his Indignation could not be too great; Men are born Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects before they are Fathers. The tender affection of a Father towards a Son is natural, and cannot be ſtifled
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:62981:71"/> without doing himſelf extream vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; however, the ſafety of his Prince is to be preferred before that of his Children; and the Voice of God to be obey'd rather than the Voice of Nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> with admirable pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bore all that <hi>Hermolaus</hi> had ſaid againſt him, and having ſeated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf where he might be heard, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd in this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Had what this Impoſtor has ſaid bin true, I could let you have torn him in pieces, and not have heard his Invectives; and were I guilty of thoſe Cruelties he charges me with, I own it I were unworthy to be King of the <hi>Macedonians.</hi> But what occaſion have I given <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molaus</hi> to ſpeak thus of me? Some time ſince he committed an inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and I caus'd him to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed according to our ancient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom; to hear him ſpeak, you would ſay, I had cruelly tormented him. What would not his Revenge
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:62981:71"/> have done, ſince for being beaten with a Whip, he could reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Parricide? 'Tis no wonder he ſhould have an horrour for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of <hi>Parmenio,</hi> of <hi>Philotas,</hi> of <hi>Aitalus,</hi> and <hi>Lynceſtes;</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending them he defends himſelf; he would not be guilty, if thoſe who have committed the ſame Crime, were declared Innocent. And as for <hi>Clitus,</hi> I wiſh I had not bin conſtrain'd to puniſh the Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his Tongue. It is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in our power to uſe Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the clemency of Kings is often times ſurmounted by the audacity of Subjects; there are certain Injuries that cannot be pardon'd. When Kings are injur'd, they muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd by Submiſſion, and not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd through Obſtinacy and Pride. I wonder not at all that <hi>Hermolaus</hi> accuſes me of Cruelty, ſince he has the impudence to accuſe me of Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice. I know Princes ought not to bear in mind the Favours they have
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:62981:72"/> beſtowed on their Subjects, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Services they have received from them. I ſhall not therefore repreſent unto you, that there are none of you but what are ſenſible of my Donatives, that would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the price of my Liberality, and the Acknowledgment you owe me. But pray conſider whence you had your Beds of Gold and Silver, your Troops of Slaves, your ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Spoils, and rich Booty. As for the <hi>Perſians,</hi> I confeſs, that coming into <hi>Aſia</hi> to conquer, not to lay deſolate, I cannot reſolve to handle as Slaves, a People whoſe Affection ſecures my Empire and your Glory; and in this I think I give ſufficient proof of my Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that I govern them in that manner, that they can have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret at my Victories. Would you be continually employ'd to ſubdue Provinces already conquer'd, which under an Imperious Dominion would be always revolting? Would
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:62981:72"/> you be ſtopp'd in the mid'ſt of your Victories by Inſurrections, better reſtrain'd by kind uſage than by force of Arms? We ſhould then extirpate whole Nations, and make our ſelves feared more for our Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, than our Courage. What glory would it be to the <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to change the Name of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, for that of Thieves and Murtherers? And after all, what have you to ſay againſt thoſe that ſight for you? In ſine, is not <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molaus</hi> wicked, to ſcoff at the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle for owning me a God? Should I refuſe a Name ſo glorious, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Will of <hi>Jupiter?</hi> as if the grandeur of my Actions did not elevate me above Men. Further, in War Reputation is worth an Army; and I could wiſh for your Glory, that the <hi>Indians</hi> would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me a God. But I ſee very well, this inſolent Youth hath ſaid nothing but what he has learnt from his Maſter <hi>Caliſthenes,</hi> and he would
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:62981:73"/> have bin glad to have heard him vent the ſame Injuries againſt me in your preſence. He is an <hi>Olynthian,</hi> and therefore I had him not brought in, becauſe the <hi>Macedonians</hi> only have the Priviledg to be try'd by the Army. As for the Criminals Relations, they ſhall live and enjoy their Charges; though I ſhould not have let theſe Parricides know this, that if they had any ſentiment of Affection for them, they might die with more regret.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> is worthy of praiſe for pardoning the Criminals Relations. It concern'd his Prudence, as well as his Bounty, ſo to do. And I am ready to think that this Law of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> inveloping the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent with the Guilty, was only made to give terror, without any deſign of putting it in execution. For what likelihood was there of maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring a number of brave Men, highly neceſſary to the State for their Valour and Experience? I ſuppoſe too, in a
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:62981:73"/> great Army, it would have bin more dangerous than eaſy to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd them. Laws are to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied as Medicines, which not rightly uſed, work a contrary effect, and bring Death inſtead of curing.</p>
               <p>After the King had diſmiſſed the Aſſembly, the Conſpirators were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd over to their Companions; who, to teſtify their fidelity, and the horror they had for the Treachery of Parricides, executed them in a cruel manner.</p>
               <p>We can learn nothing certain from Hiſtory concerning the Death of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſthenes.</hi> Some write that he died upon the Rack; others, that he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd the Rack, and was afterwards Crucified; all agree that either he liv'd a moſt miſerable Life, or dy'd a moſt cruel Death. Certain 'tis, that he was no ways Confederate in the Conſpiracy; but he was of a moroſe humour, inflexible, and very unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the Court. He would treat with the King upon equal terms, and
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:62981:74"/> ſpeak at Court as in the Schools; whence <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaid of him, <hi>That he had all the Auſterity of a Philoſopher, all the Eloquence of an Orator, but very little Conduct and Judgment.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may be ſaid, the memory of <hi>Alexander</hi> will be odious to all Ages, for cauſing to be executed a Man of an incorruptible probity, excellent in Wiſdom and Knowledg, the faireſt Ornament of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:62981:74"/>
               <head>THE CONSPIRACY OF <hi>ANTIPATER.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw are we arrived to the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of Perfidy; hitherto have bin but vain endeavours. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune was vigilant in <hi>Alexander</hi>'s pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; but at laſt ſhe delivers him over to a Traitor, who by Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hurries him out of the World, that had made himſelf Maſter of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Antipater</hi> is the Man, the more blame-worthy, as <hi>Alexander</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted him with the Kingdom of <hi>Macedonia.</hi> This Prince when he went for <hi>Aſia,</hi> left behind him his Mother <hi>Olympias,</hi> a Woman haughty, ambitious, cruel; and if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:62981:75"/> Hiſtory, Adulterous, and skill'd in Magick. He left her all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and State of a great Princeſs, and commanded <hi>Antipater</hi> to obſerve all her Motions; but to do nothing that might ſhew diſtruſt. The jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy of ſupream Authority preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly divided theſe ambitious Spirits, and the affection of the People. <hi>Antipater</hi> was the Image of their Prince, <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias</hi> his Mother; the Laws of the Kingdom defended Him, Nature pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected Her.</p>
               <p>Had <hi>Alexander</hi> foreſeen theſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, he had done like a great Prince, to leave in <hi>Macedonia</hi> theſe two Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits jealous one of another. This was the only means in his abſence to preſerve himſelf the Kingdom of his Anceſtors. To leave his Mother in abſolute Authority was dangerous; the <hi>Macedonians</hi> doubtleſs would never have yielded Obedience to a Woman; the <hi>Grecian</hi> Provinces would have revolted; and all the Neighbour Princes, jealous of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:62981:75"/> Grandeur, would have taken up Arms, and have made uſe of his abſence. On the other hand, it was to be fear'd, that if <hi>Antipater</hi> were eſtabliſhed ſole Governor of ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful a Kingdom, <hi>Olympias,</hi> as the Prince's Mother, might make a Party ſufficient to effect the ruin of the State. But the choice <hi>Alexander</hi> made of theſe two Perſons was not the effect of his Providence. For <hi>Antipater</hi> having written a Letter to him full of Invectives againſt <hi>Olym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias,</hi> he laugh'd at the reading of it, and ſaid to thoſe then preſent, <hi>That one Tear from his Mother was able to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face all the evil Impreſſions that could be given of her Conduct; that</hi> Antipater <hi>was a very bad Politician to oppoſe the Queen's Deſires; and that all</hi> Greece <hi>could not make him ſuſpect her.</hi> And <hi>Antipater</hi> having added, That <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater, Alexander</hi>'s Siſter, proſtituted her ſelf ſhamefully, and led a very diſſolute Life; he anſwered, <hi>That ſhe might make uſe of her Royal Priviledg.</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:62981:76"/> On the other hand, <hi>Olympias</hi> accuſed <hi>Antipater</hi> of Tyranny. Her Policy was to ſet <hi>Alexander</hi> againſt him, and to perſwade him, that ſhe had an intire motherly Affection for him, a true Zeal and Paſſion for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> deſiring to pleaſe his Mother, and ſuſpecting, upon the Advice ſhe had given him, <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Fidelity, takes from him the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it on <hi>Craterus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> having therefore taken from <hi>Antipater</hi> the Government of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> ſhould either have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd a Man of ſo great Credit, or have recompenced his Services. He, on the contrary, inſtead of ſending him away, calls him into the Army, and prefers his Sons, <hi>Jollas</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> to Charges, not to be intruſted but with thoſe on whom a Prince has ſhowred Favours. In the mean while he continues diſaffected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Father, irritating his
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:62981:76"/> Courage, already not well brooking the Affront given him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> glorying in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, meditated vaſt Deſigns; the extent of ſo great an Empire not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying his Ambition, he aſpir'd to the Monarchy of the Univerſe. In the mean while <hi>Antipater</hi> receiving the news of his Diſgrace, preſently conſpires the Death of his King. And remembring the unfortunate Succeſs of the Conſpiracies, both of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> and <hi>Hermolaus,</hi> he avoided the Precipice into which they fell. He took other meaſures, and thought Poiſon an infallible means to diſpatch <hi>Alexander.</hi> Some write that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> gave him this Advice. But as for me, I cannot imagine that Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher capable of ſo great a Villany againſt his Pupil, and his King, who had loaded him with Favours. The Example of <hi>Seneca,</hi> who according to all appearance conſpir'd the Death of <hi>Nero,</hi> proves nothing againſt <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> he only made profeſſion
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:62981:77"/> of Wiſdom; the other aſpir'd to an Empire.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Death being reſolv'd upon, <hi>Antipater</hi> ſent his Son <hi>Caſſander</hi> to the Army, intending ſpeedily to follow him; and charg'd him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the King how falſe and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Olympias</hi> her Accuſations were. Coming to the Army near <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>Perſians</hi> proſtrate themſelves at the King's feet, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan openly to ſcoff at them, and could not forbear laughing; which ſo offended the King, that he took him by the Hair of his Head, drag'd him on the Ground, and trampl'd on him. Some days after <hi>Caſſander</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving undertaken his Father's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt thoſe that were come to accuſe him, the King commanded him to hold his peace; ſaying, <hi>'Twas very unlikely Men ſhould come ſo far to tell him Lies. Caſſander</hi> would continue, but <hi>Alexander</hi> told him in choler, <hi>That he would make him repent of his Diſobedience; that his Reaſons
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:62981:77"/> were no other than</hi> Ariſtotle'<hi>s Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and that he would not ſuffer</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater, <hi>vain and treacherous as he was, to go unpuniſh'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after this <hi>Antipater</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd. He ſaw the Storm hovering over his Head, and thought how he might prevent the Danger. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he call'd his Sons, <hi>Caſſander, Jollas,</hi> and <hi>Philip;</hi> and with all the authority and tenderneſs of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, repreſents unto them, <q>That in vain he had given them Being, if he did not endeavour to procure them a Life full of Happineſs and Pleaſure; and that he ſhould be himſelf very unhappy if he did not live after his Death in his Children, ſucceeding him in his Revenues and Imploiments. Thoſe, <hi>ſaid he,</hi> have no reaſon to applaud Nature, that are born of an Illuſtrious Race, and live unfortunately; the more ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did their Birth, the more heavy and inſupportable is their Miſery. As Man is a part of the Univerſe,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:62981:78"/> through the qualities of his Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments and his Spirits; ſo he is no part of the World Politick, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Riches and Promotions. To be without theſe, is not to live, but to die, nay, to die every day as long as ones Life laſts. Theſe Thoughts, my dear Children, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb me only upon your account. You know what great Glory I have acquir'd in the Armies, which gain'd me a large ſhare in <hi>Philip</hi>'s Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You have ſeen me rais'd to the higheſt degree of Grandeur, Arbiter of a flouriſhing Kingdom; careſſed by <hi>Alexander,</hi> till ſuch time as his mind of late, as much corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the effeminacy of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> as it was formerly well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by the Precepts of Divine <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> induc'd him to depoſe me from governing <hi>Macedonia;</hi> and upon the Report of my Enemies to ſuſpect my Fidelity, always incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible. So that 'tis impoſſible to ſupport our Grandeur, unleſs we
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:62981:78"/> take off the Head of this Monſter. Can you be of ſo baſe a Spirit, as to reſolve to live unhappy, without Wealth, without Honour? Can you be ſo unnatural as to ſurvive my Misfortune? What ſay I? Can you think to eſcape Death, after they have taken away my Life? <hi>Caſſander,</hi> thou haſt had experience of this Tyrant's Cruelty, thou haſt heard his Threats; Canſt thou doubt of ſuddenly ſeeing the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects? <hi>Olympias,</hi> infamous as ſhe is, has prevail'd againſt our Merit; ſhall we wait, like <hi>Clitus</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menio,</hi> to be ſacrific'd to <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Fury? No; I can never think that the Off-ſpring of <hi>Antipater</hi> will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from his Glory, and that of his Anceſtors. Be not daunted at the Death of <hi>Philotas</hi> and <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molaus:</hi> like a good Pilot I have learnt to avoid thoſe Rocks where others have bin Shipwrack'd. Thoſe were forc'd to have ſeveral Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates, to intruſt a Secret to many
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:62981:79"/> Perſons; we our ſelves can execute the Deſign I meditate. They would have kill'd <hi>Alexander</hi> in the midſt of his Guards, in the ſight of the the Army; We will take him off by Poiſon at Table, in the midſt of good Cheer. His Sickneſs and his Death will be imputed to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauching. <hi>Jollas</hi> is his chief Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearer, what is there more eaſy, than to convey the Poiſon into his Wine, or into his Water? My dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, 'tis now no longer time to deliberate, we muſt ſpeedily kill <hi>Alexander,</hi> or he will kill us.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſſander, Jollas,</hi> and <hi>Philip,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reſolv'd upon that great Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany, and expected only the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niency of ſome Feaſt, that they might execute their Deſign.</p>
               <p>In the mean while <hi>Alexander</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens towards <hi>Babylon,</hi> where Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors from all parts of the World attended his coming, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate with him for his Conqueſts. <hi>Nearchus,</hi> one of his chief Officers,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:62981:79"/> advertiſed him of a Prediction of the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> threatning him with inevitable peril if he enter'd the City <hi>Babylon.</hi> Though he was as much given to Superſtition as any one, yet nothing could ſtop his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. In appearance he went thither as to the Diet of the Univerſe, to impoſe Laws on all the Earth; but in reality his Deſtiny drew him, thither he went to his own deſtruction.</p>
               <p>As he drew near the Walls of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> ſeveral Preſages troubled him, and he remember'd the counſel of <hi>Nearchus.</hi> Nevertheleſs he would not return back, but entred the City, foreſeeing, as it were, his Misfortune. Not long after a <hi>Theſſalian</hi> Phyſician made a Feaſt, and invited <hi>Alexander</hi> and the chief of his Courtiers thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He failed not to be there, and having drank of <hi>Hercules</hi> his Cup, he felt ſuch violent pain, that he deſir'd them to kill him with his Sword. It was preſently given out, that drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too much Wine had occaſion'd his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:62981:80"/> Diſtemper; and thus <hi>Antipater</hi>'s Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſtifled the Infamy of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> writes, that <hi>Alexander</hi> died of a violent Feaver; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports for proof of what he alleages, that his Body continued for ſeveral days as freſh and ſound, as at the moment of his expiring. I wonder that ſo Learned a Man ſhould be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the nature of ſome Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that preſerve from corrupting, and leave no marks of their effect. Whatſoever may be ſaid, 'tis certain that perfidious <hi>Jollas</hi> poiſon'd the King's Water, and then mix'd it with his Wine.</p>
               <p>Thus expir'd great <hi>Alexander,</hi> quell'd by Domeſtick Treaſon, after he had conquer'd all the <hi>Eaſt.</hi> The eminent Qualities appearing in him at the beginning of his Reign, made every one admire him; the enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Vices, proceeding from his Fortune, render'd him odious to all the World. He continu'd a long
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:62981:80"/> time magnificent, liberal, of a ſweet and gentle diſpoſition, inclin'd to Juſtice and Clemency; he became at once unjuſt, cruel, extravagant, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtful, ſuperſtitious, and ſo addicted to all ſorts of Vice, that there was no hopes of his returning.</p>
               <p>So Illuſtious an Example as this, may ſerve to inſtruct all Princes, that there is no Power ſtronger than a reſolute Heart; that there is no Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence but may be o're-reach'd by Malice; and that the Diſpair of one Man is more to be fear'd than an Army.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:62981:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62981:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62981:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62981:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62981:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62981:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62981:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62981:7"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62981:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62981:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62981:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:62981:9"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62981:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62981:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62981:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62981:11"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62981:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:62981:12"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:62981:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62981:13"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:62981:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62981:14"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62981:15"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62981:15"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62981:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62981:16"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62981:17"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:62981:17"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62981:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62981:18"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62981:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62981:19"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:62981:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:62981:20"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
